<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>My website | Esteban Solano G.</title>
  <icon>https://www.gravatar.com/avatar/7684419e419d24da06e55c3fde6b7317</icon>
  <subtitle>Software Engineer at Microsoft | Former MVP, Certified developer</subtitle>
  <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.539Z</updated>
  <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Esteban Solano G.</name>
    <email>stvansolano@outlook.com</email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resumen - Novedades Microsoft Ignite, GitHub Universe y .NET Conf 2023!</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2023/11/18/Resumen-noviembre-2023-Ignite-GitHub-dotNetConf/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2023/11/18/Resumen-noviembre-2023-Ignite-GitHub-dotNetConf/</id>
    <published>2023-11-18T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.539Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Resumen de eventos del mes sobre recientes novedades e innovaciones en el mundo de tecnología y trabajo colaborativo: Microsoft Ignite 2023, GitHub Universe y .NET Conf 2023!</p><!-- more --><p>Estos eventos son grandes oportunidades para aprender de expertos, afilar nuestras habilidades y descubrir lo que viene en el futuro en diferentes tecnologías en torno a la productividad, trabajo colaborativo en la nube, la inteligencia artificial, el desarrollo de plataformas entorno a Azure, M365, Windows y el auge de las tecnologias de desarrollo web, movil y de escritorio.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2023/11/18/Resumen-noviembre-2023-Ignite-GitHub-dotNetConf/preview.png" alt="Preview" title="Preview" /><h2 id="Sobre-NET-Conf-2023-dotNetConf"><a href="#Sobre-NET-Conf-2023-dotNetConf" class="headerlink" title="Sobre .NET Conf 2023 - dotNetConf"></a>Sobre .NET Conf 2023 - dotNetConf</h2><p>En especial cada año la .NET Conf, revela las principales novedades de desarrollo de aplicaciones con dicha tecnología, nuevas versiones, mejoras y tendencias aplicadas año a año para mejorar la experiencia de desarrollo y programación con C#, F#, VB, entre otros.</p><p>Otro de los anuncios más destacados fue el lanzamiento oficial del tan esperado <strong>.NET 8</strong>, la nueva versión del stack de código abierto de Microsoft ofrece mejoras de rendimiento, seguridad, productividad y compatibilidad. .NET 8 permite desarrollar aplicaciones web completamente con el stack de .NET y <strong>Blazor</strong>, sacandole provecho al renderizado en el lado del servidor y la interactividad en el lado del cliente. Además, .NET 8 introduce las novedades de <strong>C# 12</strong>, como las expresiones de colección y los constructores primarios.</p><h2 id="La-era-de-los-Copilots-Microsoft-GitHub-Copilots"><a href="#La-era-de-los-Copilots-Microsoft-GitHub-Copilots" class="headerlink" title="La era de los Copilots! Microsoft + GitHub Copilots"></a>La era de los Copilots! Microsoft + GitHub Copilots</h2><p>Uno de los anuncios más importantes que se hicieron en ambos eventos fue el lanzamiento de <strong>Microsoft Copilot</strong>, una solución de inteligencia artificial que ayuda a los usuarios a optimizar sus procesos de negocio, mejorar su productividad y crear experiencias personalizadas. De lo más destacado, Microsoft Copilot se integra con Windows 11, el nuevo sistema operativo que ofrece características impulsadas por la inteligencia artificial, como Bing Chat Enterprise, una función que permite conversar con Bing en modo chat.</p><blockquote><p>Microsoft Copilot se conecta con Microsoft 365, la suite de productividad que incluye aplicaciones como Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook y Teams!</p></blockquote><p>Además durante el Ignite 2023, Microsoft anunció las inversiones actuales y futuras para ofrecer una experiencia de Windows segura, flexible y fluida a los empleados y contratistas con <strong>Azure Virtual Desktop</strong> y <strong>Windows 365</strong>. Estas soluciones permiten acceder a un escritorio virtual de Windows desde cualquier dispositivo y lugar, con la máxima seguridad y eficiencia.</p><p>Durante este mismo mes, se celebro GitHub Universe 2023, mucho mas enfocado a las novedades e innovaciones en torno al mundo de GitHub. Y porsupuesto, mas avances en inteligencia artificial y Copilots! Uno de los anuncios mas importantes fue GitHub Copilot Chat, herramienta que permite a los usuarios utilizar los grandes modelos de lenguaje (sigas en ingles LLM - Large Language models) natural como una manera universal para poder programar, resolver problemas y automatizar procesos tipicos de programacion y desarrollo de sistemas.</p><blockquote><p>GitHub Copilot Chat estara disponible en Diciembre 2023! Mas detalles en <a href="https://github.blog/2023-11-08-universe-2023-copilot-transforms-github-into-the-ai-powered-developer-platform/">https://github.blog/2023-11-08-universe-2023-copilot-transforms-github-into-the-ai-powered-developer-platform/</a></p></blockquote><p>Si te perdiste estos eventos, puedes ver las grabaciones de las sesiones y los recursos adicionales en los sitios web oficiales de Microsoft Ignite, GitHub Universe y .NET 2023 en línea!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Resumen de eventos del mes sobre recientes novedades e innovaciones en el mundo de tecnología y trabajo colaborativo: Microsoft Ignite 2023, GitHub Universe y .NET Conf 2023!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Productividad" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Productividad/"/>
    
    <category term="M365" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/M365/"/>
    
    <category term="AI" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/AI/"/>
    
    <category term="GitHub" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/GitHub/"/>
    
    <category term="Windows" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Windows/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>El futuro del trabajo en 2023 - Presentando Microsoft 365 Copilot</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2023/03/24/El-futuro-del-trabajo-presentando-M365-copilot/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2023/03/24/El-futuro-del-trabajo-presentando-M365-copilot/</id>
    <published>2023-03-24T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.507Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Presentando Microsoft 365 Copilot: Combina tus datos de la nube disponibles en Microsoft Graph con la tecnología de inteligencia artificial!</p><!-- more --><p>Nos encontramos en un momento de la historia del trabajo donde la máxima aspiración es la productividad y la eficiencia del tiempo. Lamentablemente dejamos de la lado (a veces por su costo o su tiempo ‘extra’ que requiere) aspectos como la creatividad y el arte a cuestas de lograr las cosas a tiempo y cumplir con las entregas.</p><p>¿Cómo lograr re-balancear y dejar de lado la carga cognitiva de nuestro trabajo para re-enfocarnos en lo que importa y sentir que le sacamos provecho a todas sus actividades cotidianas?</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="360" height="202" src="2023/03/24/El-futuro-del-trabajo-presentando-M365-copilot/preview.webp" alt="Preview" title="Preview" /><blockquote><p><strong>Spoiler:</strong> Trabajo como ingeniero de software en Microsoft (por cierto, hay vacantes abiertas para Latam! Contactame por [LinkedIn] (<a href="http://cr.linkedin.com/in/stvansolano">http://cr.linkedin.com/in/stvansolano</a>)). Las palabras en este artículo son de mi autoría y pueden no reflejar las opiniones de la compañía o sus socios 🙂</p></blockquote><p>Bueno, el futuro del trabajo en 2023 esta siendo tomado cada vez más por los automatas inteligentes que, lejos de quitarnos el trabajo, buscan poder aliviar la carga laboral y permitirnos echarle mano más a la creatividad y la excelencia. El pasado 20 de marzo Microsoft presentó las iniciativas ‘Copilot’ para la suite de Office 365 y muchos de los productos ampliamente conocidos como Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook, Teams, entre otros que van a verse redimensionados con asistentes cada vez más inteligente y capaces de sacarle el jugo a nuestro trabajo de la mano de Inteligencia Artificial. Puedes ver la grabación del event [aca] (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/events/7038508574142074880/">https://www.linkedin.com/events/7038508574142074880/</a>) (inglés).</p><p>En palabras de Jared Spartaro durante el evento, estamos ante una forma de re-conectar con el alma de nuestro trabajo y una nueva etapa de como interactuamos con las computadoras.</p><h2 id="Presentando-Microsoft-365-Copilot"><a href="#Presentando-Microsoft-365-Copilot" class="headerlink" title="Presentando Microsoft 365 Copilot:"></a>Presentando Microsoft 365 Copilot:</h2><p>Microsoft 365 Copilot combina tus datos de la nube disponibles en Microsoft Graph con la tecnología de LLM (Large Language Models o Grandes Modelos de Lenguaje) para realizar cómputo en segundos mediante lenguaje natural y un estilo conversacional asistido por Copiloto, el cual estará disponible en toda la suite de herramientas de productividad mediante la función Business Chat para ponernos al día, generar contenido y automatizar muchas de las actividades derivadas como agendar, generar reportes (contenidos, etc) y extenderlo con herramientas automatizadas como flujos de trabajo con Power Apps.</p><p>Los pilares que utiliza esta tecnología estan basados en los principios de Seguridad, Compliance, Privacidad y la Inteligencia Artificial (Responsible AI), lo cual hace que esten listos para utilizarce en la empresa y nuestra vida personal.</p><p>Una de las características mas resaltadas es el uso integrado de Copilot en Teams, el cual puede utilizarse de diferentes modos para interactuar con contenido como Documentos, Contactos, Correo electrónico, entre otros. </p><p>Si estás familiarizado con la tecnología de Copilot en GitHub, (que recientemente anuncio que ya esta utilizando ChatGPT 4!), la cual fue introducida desde hace un tiempo ya, ha demostrado ser de gran utilidad para los desarrolladores para automatizar labores ordinarias, revisar código y facilitar la automatización en función de concentrarnos en el trabajo de fondo y de pensamiento analítico. </p><p>Más recientemente, con la introducción de GPT 4&#x2F;3, LLMs y los chatbots cada vez más inteligentes, muchas de estas estas capacidades toman mayor fuerza e impacto en la productividad de nuestro trabajo del día a día.</p><h2 id="Como-funciona-Lenguaje-natural"><a href="#Como-funciona-Lenguaje-natural" class="headerlink" title="Cómo funciona: Lenguaje natural."></a>Cómo funciona: Lenguaje natural.</h2><p>¿Cómo lo hace? Copilot introduce el lenguaje natural, tal cual como dialogar y entender el contexto de una conversación sobre lo que necesitas, y poder desplegar contenido como redactar un email, resumir un documento u otros contenidos y poderte poner al día de toda la carga (entiendase más contexto y ocasiones ruido) derivado del ambiente laboral digital, el cual puede ser abrumador en ocasiones.</p><p>Basta con ver algunos de los demos para darse una idea del gran potencial y las características que se han ido liberando en el mismo buscador de Bing.</p><h2 id="Demo-PowerPoint"><a href="#Demo-PowerPoint" class="headerlink" title="Demo: PowerPoint"></a>Demo: PowerPoint</h2><p>De mis características favoritas, la posibilidad de dar contexto dd la situación a Copilot y generar contenido basado en ello y los documentos de la nube es de los mejores que incorpora Copilot, permitiendo colapsar, ampliar o darle toques al tono del texto (neutral, profesional, casual) justo antes de poderlo enviar, ya sea como borrador y cambiaro posteriormente por ejemplo en propuestas de negocio, muy común cuando hay poco tiempo de preparación o nevesitas aplicar los formatos comunes o de uso en la empresa. ¿Cuántas veces te ha pasado que tienes que montar una PPT desde un documento que ya tenias hecho en Word? ¡Ahora puedes hacerlo desde unas cuantas instrucciones desde Copilot! </p><blockquote><p>Video: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fzoZ_f7ji5Q">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fzoZ_f7ji5Q</a> (ingles)</p></blockquote><p>Con todo ello, te invito a mantenerte de cerca con los anuncios, la próxima &#x2F;&#x2F;Build 2023 (formato híbrido!) que ya anunció la apertura del registro y a que me cuentes tus impresiones. ¿Crees que transformará el trabajo como lo conocemos? </p><p>Seguimos en contacto!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Presentando Microsoft 365 Copilot: Combina tus datos de la nube disponibles en Microsoft Graph con la tecnología de inteligencia artificial!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Productividad" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Productividad/"/>
    
    <category term="ChatGPT" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/ChatGPT/"/>
    
    <category term="M365" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/M365/"/>
    
    <category term="AI" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/AI/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The future of work - Introducing Microsoft 365 Copilot 🤖</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2023/03/24/The-future-of-work-introducing-microsoft-365-copilot/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2023/03/24/The-future-of-work-introducing-microsoft-365-copilot/</id>
    <published>2023-03-24T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.555Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Introducing Microsoft 365 Copilot: Combine your cloud data available in Microsoft Graph with artificial intelligence technology! </p><!-- more --><p>We are at a moment in the history of work where the maximum aspiration is productivity and time efficiency. Unfortunately, sometimes we tend to leave aside (sometimes due to its cost or extra time required) aspects like creativity and art in order to achieve things on time and meet deadlines. </p><p>How to achieve rebalancing and leaving aside the cognitive load of our work to refocus on what matters and feel that we take advantage of all the daily activities of work? </p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="360" height="202" src="2023/03/24/The-future-of-work-introducing-microsoft-365-copilot/preview.webp" alt="Preview" title="Preview" /><p>Well, the future of work in 2023 is increasingly being taken over by intelligent bots that, far from taking our jobs away, seek to relieve the workload and allow us to make more use of creativity and excellence. On March 16th, 2023 Microsoft presented the ‘Copilot’ initiatives for the Office 365 suite and many widely known products such as Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook, Teams, among others that will be resized with an increasingly intelligent assistant capable of getting the most out of our work with Artificial Intelligence. You can watch the event recording <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/events/7038508574142074880/">here.</a></p><p>In Jared Spartaro’s words during the event, we are finding a way to reconnect with the soul of our work and a new stage of how we interact with computers. </p><h2 id="Introducing-Microsoft-365-Copilot"><a href="#Introducing-Microsoft-365-Copilot" class="headerlink" title="Introducing Microsoft 365 Copilot:"></a>Introducing Microsoft 365 Copilot:</h2><p>Microsoft 365 Copilot combines your cloud data available in Microsoft Graph with LLM (Large Language Models) technology to perform natural language computing and conversational style assisted by Copilot, which will be available throughout the suite of productivity tools through Business Chat to keep us up to date, generate content and automate many of the derived activities such as scheduling, sending reports (contents, etc.), extending it with automated tools such as workflows with Power Apps. </p><p>The pillars used by this technology are based on the principles of Security, Compliance, Privacy and Artificial Intelligence (Responsible AI), which makes them ready for use in business and personal life. One of the most highlighted features is the integrated use of Copilot in Teams, which can be used in different ways to interact with content such as Documents, Contacts, Email, among others. If you are familiar with Copilot technology on GitHub, which was recently announced (already being used by ChatGPT 4!), which was introduced some time ago, it has proven to be very useful for developers to automate ordinary tasks, review code and facilitate automation in order to focus on background work. </p><p>More recently, with the introduction of ChatGPT 4&#x2F;3, LLMs and increasingly intelligent chatbots, many of these capabilities gain greater strength and impact on the productivity of our day-to-day work.</p><h2 id="How-it-works-Natural-language"><a href="#How-it-works-Natural-language" class="headerlink" title="How it works: Natural language."></a>How it works: Natural language.</h2><p>How does it do it? Copilot introduces natural language, just like having a conversation and understanding the context of a conversation about what you need, and being able to display content such as writing an email, summarizing a document or other content and being able to keep up with all the load (understand more context and noise occasions) derived from the digital work environment, which can be overwhelming at times.</p><p>Just look at some of the demos to get an idea of the great potential and features that have been released in the same Bing search engine.</p><h2 id="Demo-PowerPoint"><a href="#Demo-PowerPoint" class="headerlink" title="Demo: PowerPoint"></a>Demo: PowerPoint</h2><p>Of my favorite features, the ability to give context to Copilot’s situation and generate content based on it and cloud documents is one of the best that Copilot incorporates, allowing you to collapse, expand or give touches to the tone of the text (neutral, professional, casual) just before you can send it. Or save it as a draft to edit later, for example in business proposals when there is little preparation time or apply common or company formats. How many times have you had to put together a PPT from a document you already had in Word? Now you can do it with just a few instructions from Copilot!</p><blockquote><p>Video: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fzoZ_f7ji5Q">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fzoZ_f7ji5Q</a> (ingles)</p></blockquote><p>With all of this, let’s stay tunned on upcoming announcements and attend the next &#x2F;&#x2F;Build 2023 (hibrid format!) which now has registration opened! I would enjoy to hear from your impressions. Do you think it’s going to change the work as we know it?</p><p>Let’s keep in touch!</p><p>Additional links:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/microsoft-365-copilot-enables-digital-assistants-weve-bob-o-donnell/">Microsoft 365 Copilot Enables the Digital Assistants We’ve Always Wanted</a></li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Introducing Microsoft 365 Copilot: Combine your cloud data available in Microsoft Graph with artificial intelligence technology!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Productividad" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Productividad/"/>
    
    <category term="ChatGPT" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/ChatGPT/"/>
    
    <category term="M365" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/M365/"/>
    
    <category term="AI" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/AI/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Exam passed! DP-900: Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals Certification</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/09/22/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Azure-Data-Fundamentals-Certification/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/09/22/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Azure-Data-Fundamentals-Certification/</id>
    <published>2022-09-22T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.511Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exam passed! DP-900: Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals - Sharing my notes and experience of earning the certification exam</p><!-- more --><h2 id="About-the-exam-Microsoft-Azure-Data-Fundamentals-DP-900-Certification"><a href="#About-the-exam-Microsoft-Azure-Data-Fundamentals-DP-900-Certification" class="headerlink" title="About the exam: Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals DP-900 Certification"></a>About the exam: Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals DP-900 Certification</h2><p>This exam is part of the 900 family which is targeted for general-purpose &#x2F; fundamentals knowledge. I enjoyed prepared for this exam as it really covers the basics for  understanding of data, which some minimum understanding of Azure offering for Data Services. Here are some of the topics I highlight:</p><ul><li>Understanding of Relational vs NoSQL and data-modelying types (structured, semi-structured, unstructured)</li><li>OLTP and OLAP concepts</li><li>Azure Storage, Data Lake and HDInsight</li><li>Azure Data Factory, Databricks and Synapse (Spark, Hadoop)</li><li>CosmosDB basics and APIs (MongoDB, Gremlim, Cassandra, SQL API)</li><li>Power BI basics including visualizations, PowerBI Service and PowerBI Desktop</li></ul><p><a href="https://www.credly.com/badges/03deb74e-54f6-4bc6-b1bc-ec8ffd8999d5/public_url"><img src="/2022/09/22/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Azure-Data-Fundamentals-Certification/preview.webp" alt="Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals DP-900 -Image"></a></p><blockquote><p>Verified by <a href="https://www.credly.com/badges/03deb74e-54f6-4bc6-b1bc-ec8ffd8999d5">Credly</a></p></blockquote><p>Earners of the Azure Data Fundamentals certification have demonstrated foundational knowledge of core data concepts and how they are implemented using Microsoft Azure data services.</p><ul><li>Describe core data concepts</li><li>Identify considerations for relational data on Azure</li><li>Describe considerations for working with non-relational data on Azure</li><li>Describe an analytics workload on Azure</li></ul><h3 id="Skills-measured"><a href="#Skills-measured" class="headerlink" title="Skills measured:"></a>Skills measured:</h3><ul><li>Describe ways to represent data, including structured,  semi-structured and unstructured data</li><li>Identify options for data storage, common formats for data files and types of databases</li><li>Describe common data workloads including both transactional and analytical workloads</li><li>Identify roles and responsibilities for data workloads including database administrators, data engineers and data analysts</li><li>Identify relational concepts SQL and NoSQL data</li></ul><p><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/dp-900?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/dp-900</a></p><h2 id="My-experience-taking-exams-online-through-Microsoft-Learning"><a href="#My-experience-taking-exams-online-through-Microsoft-Learning" class="headerlink" title="My experience taking exams online through Microsoft Learning"></a>My experience taking exams online through Microsoft Learning</h2><p>If you are interested, I’ve put together some recommendations for taking this kind of certification exams as part of my <a href="/2021/11/20/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Artificial-Intelligence-Fundamentals-AI-900-certification/">Microsoft AI Fundamentals AI-900 Certification post here</a> which I recommend to take a look on preparing for exam day.</p><h2 id="Recommended-resources-for-exam"><a href="#Recommended-resources-for-exam" class="headerlink" title="Recommended resources for exam"></a>Recommended resources for exam</h2><p>Here is a list of materials to take a look in case you are considering to pursuit the certification, which is available from Microsoft Learn website:</p><ul><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-core-data-concepts/">https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-core-data-concepts/</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-relational-data/">https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-relational-data/</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-non-relational-data/">https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-non-relational-data/</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-data-warehouse-analytics/">https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-data-warehouse-analytics/</a></li></ul><p>See the full list and additional content at: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/dp-900">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/dp-900</a></p><h2 id="Deep-links-Basics-trainings-and-recommended-lectures"><a href="#Deep-links-Basics-trainings-and-recommended-lectures" class="headerlink" title="Deep links - Basics, trainings and recommended lectures"></a>Deep links - Basics, trainings and recommended lectures</h2><ul><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/synapse-analytics/overview-what-is">What is Azure Synapse Analytics? - Azure Synapse Analytics</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/power-bi/guidance/star-schema">Understand star schema and the importance for Power BI - Power BI</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/storageservices/Understanding-the-Table-Service-Data-Model">Understanding the Table service data model (REST API) - Azure Storage</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-fundamentals-stream-processing/2-batch-stream">Understand batch and stream processing - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/architecture/guide/architecture-styles/big-data">Big data architecture style - Azure Architecture Center</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/architecture/cloud-native/relational-vs-nosql-data">Relational vs. NoSQL data</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/storage/blobs/access-tiers-overview?tabs=azure-portal">Hot, Cool, and Archive access tiers for blob data - Azure Storage</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/examine-components-of-modern-data-warehouse/3-data-ingestion-pipelines">Explore data ingestion pipelines - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-factory/introduction">Introduction to Azure Data Factory - Azure Data Factory</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-non-relational-data-stores-azure/3-cosmos-db-apis">Identify Azure Cosmos DB APIs - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/sql/tutorial-query-sql-api">Tutorial: How to query with SQL in Azure Cosmos DB?</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/table/tutorial-query-table">How to query table data in Azure Cosmos DB?</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/graph/tutorial-query-graph">How to query graph data in Azure Cosmos DB?</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-factory/how-to-invoke-ssis-package-ssis-activity?tabs=data-factory">Use the Execute SSIS Package activity from the portal - Azure Data Factory</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-factory/connector-overview">Connector overview - Azure Data Factory &amp; Azure Synapse</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/table/introduction">Introduction to the Azure Cosmos DB Table API</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/graph/graph-introduction">Introduction to Azure Cosmos DB Gremlin API</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/cassandra/cassandra-introduction">Introduction to the Azure Cosmos DB Cassandra API</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-core-data-concepts/5-transactional-data-processing">Explore transactional data processing - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/architecture/data-guide/relational-data/online-analytical-processing">Online analytical processing (OLAP) - Azure Architecture Center</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-fundamentals-data-visualization/3-data-modeling">Describe core concepts of data modeling - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/introduction-power-bi/2a-data-modeling-visualizations">Data modeling and visualizations - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/power-bi/fundamentals/desktop-getting-started">Get started with Power BI Desktop - Power BI</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/postgresql/single-server/concepts-azure-ad-authentication">Active Directory authentication - Azure Database for PostgreSQL - Single Server</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/postgresql/single-server/concepts-ssl-connection-security">SSL&#x2F;TLS - Azure Database for PostgreSQL - Single Server</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/postgresql/hyperscale/howto-ssl-connection-security">Transport Layer Security (TLS) - Hyperscale (Citus) - Azure Database for PostgreSQL</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/postgresql/single-server/overview">What is Azure Database for PostgreSQL</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/architecture/guide/technology-choices/data-store-overview">Understand data store models - Azure Application Architecture Guide</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-provision-deploy-non-relational-data-services-azure/">Explore Azure Storage for non-relational data - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/storage/blobs/data-lake-storage-introduction">Azure Data Lake Storage Gen2 Introduction</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/databricks/scenarios/what-is-azure-databricks">What is Azure Databricks?</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/hdinsight/hdinsight-overview">What is Azure HDInsight</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/storage/common/storage-redundancy">Data redundancy - Azure Storage</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/azure-data-fundamentals-explore-non-relational-data/">Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals: Explore non-relational data in Azure - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-sql/migration-guides/managed-instance/sql-server-to-managed-instance-overview?view=azuresql">SQL Server to SQL Managed Instance: Migration overview - Azure SQL Managed Instance</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-provision-deploy-relational-database-offerings-azure/2-azure-sql">Describe Azure SQL services and capabilities - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-sql/database/features-comparison?view=azuresql">Compare the database engine features of SQL Database and SQL Managed Instance - Azure SQL Database &amp; SQL Managed Instance</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/azure-sql/managed-instance/sql-managed-instance-paas-overview?view=azuresql">What is Azure SQL Managed Instance? - Azure SQL Managed Instance</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-relational-data-offerings/">Explore fundamental relational data concepts - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://powerbi.microsoft.com/en-us/">Data Visualization | Microsoft Power BI</a></li><li><a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/products/azure-sql/database/">Azure SQL Database – Managed Cloud Database Service | Microsoft Azure</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-fundamentals-stream-processing/3-explore-common-elements">Explore common elements of stream processing architecture - Training</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/synapse-analytics/spark/apache-spark-overview">Apache Spark in Azure Synapse Analytics overview - Azure Synapse Analytics</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/databricks/structured-streaming/">What is Apache Spark Structured Streaming? - Azure Databricks</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/power-bi/fundamentals/service-service-vs-desktop">Comparing Power BI Desktop and the Power BI service - Power BI</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/storage/blobs/storage-blobs-introduction">Introduction to Blob (object) storage - Azure Storage</a></li><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/explore-provision-deploy-non-relational-data-services-azure/2-azure-blob-storage">Explore Azure blob storage - Training</a></li></ul><p>I would be more than happy to connect in case you want to get more tips for getting ready for the exam. Please feel free to reach out to my <a href="http://cr.linkedin.com/in/stvansolano">LinkedIn here</a></p><p>-Esteban</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Microsoft Certified: Microsoft Azure Data Fundamentals was issued to Esteban Solano Granados</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
    <category term="Exam" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Exam/"/>
    
    <category term="Certification" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Certification/"/>
    
    <category term="Data" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Data/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Create a React-based app with ASP.NET Minimal APIs and MongoDB storage</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/06/20/Creating-a-react-app-with-AspNet-Minimal-APIs-and-MongoDb-CosmosDb/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/06/20/Creating-a-react-app-with-AspNet-Minimal-APIs-and-MongoDb-CosmosDb/</id>
    <published>2022-06-20T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.507Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been using React for while by mixing it up with .NET stuff and enjoying it a lot. For this post, I decided to combine them along with Docker Compose, ASP.NET Minimal APIs and MongoDB support!</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Using-React"><a href="#Using-React" class="headerlink" title="Using React"></a>Using React</h2><p>I use React the tech behind my blog (mostly NodeJS&#x2F;Jamstack client-side generated which I migrated recently from existing code that has been around ~2015) both for the client and server side rendering.</p><p>So this time I decided to set a sample to combine React and .NET in a sample app and ended-up packing it as <a href="https://github.com/docker/awesome-compose/pull/248">Pull-Request #248</a> for the <a href="https://github.com/docker/awesome-compose">Awesome-Compose</a> repo from Docker in GitHub, following same structure I did for previous .NET contributions into that repo. </p><p>If you are interested in previous posts about Awesome-Compose, either curious about Docker-izing .NET 5&#x2F;6 apps or using GitHub Codespaces for development you can browse them from <a href="/2022/03/24/Upgrading-dotnet-5-to-6-using-minimal-apis-and-github-codespaces/">here</a> and <a href="/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/">here</a>.</p><p>The code for this post is also available from my GitHub under this repo:</p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/codebox-react-dotnet-mongodb">https://github.com/stvansolano/codebox-react-dotnet-mongodb</a></p><p>So, let’s get started! A few things you may need to install: </p><ul><li>Docker Compose</li><li>.NET 6 SDK</li><li>NodeJS</li></ul><blockquote><p><strong>Side-note:</strong> I didn’t really have to install anything while developing this on my local as I was using GitHub Codespaces with my some tailored <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/stvansolano/codebox-react-dotnet-mongodb/main/.devcontainer/Dockerfile">devcontainer</a> setup, so I can focus on development!</p></blockquote><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="360" height="202" src="/2022/06/20/Creating-a-react-app-with-AspNet-Minimal-APIs-and-MongoDb-CosmosDb/preview.webp" alt="Preview" title="Preview" /><h2 id="1-Creating-the-x2F-frontend-A-simple-TODO-app"><a href="#1-Creating-the-x2F-frontend-A-simple-TODO-app" class="headerlink" title="1) Creating the &#x2F;frontend: A simple TODO app."></a>1) Creating the &#x2F;frontend: A simple TODO app.</h2><p>For this sample, we will use <code>react-scripts</code> scaffold for creating a basic app and use a very simple, still classic sample for having a TODO app in order to focus on JavaScript, NodeJS&#x2F;Npx stuff. For this sample, I also re-used pretty much of the React sample from Awesome-Compose repo, which is fairly common and straightforward:</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="183" height="400" src="/2022/06/20/Creating-a-react-app-with-AspNet-Minimal-APIs-and-MongoDb-CosmosDb/frontend-structure.webp" alt="Frontend structure" title="Frontend structure" /><p>In order to consume our API later from ASP.NET, let’s add a NGINX file for taking care of the API calls later from our ASP.NET Web API. Things will run on their own NGINX-based container so the backend is de-coupled from the frontend.</p><figure class="highlight yaml"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line"><span class="string">server</span> &#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">listen</span>       <span class="number">80</span><span class="string">;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">server_name</span>  <span class="string">localhost;</span></span><br><span class="line">    </span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">server_tokens</span> <span class="string">off;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">proxy_hide_header</span> <span class="string">X-Powered-By;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">proxy_hide_header</span> <span class="string">Server;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">X-XSS-Protection</span> <span class="string">&quot;1; mode=block&quot;</span><span class="string">;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">Strict-Transport-Security</span> <span class="string">&#x27;max-age=31536000; includeSubDomains; preload&#x27;</span><span class="string">;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">X-Frame-Options</span> <span class="string">DENY;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">X-Content-Type-Options</span> <span class="string">nosniff;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">X-Permitted-Cross-Domain-Policies</span> <span class="string">master-only;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">Referrer-Policy</span> <span class="string">same-origin;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">add_header</span> <span class="string">Expect-CT</span> <span class="string">&#x27;max-age=60&#x27;</span><span class="string">;</span></span><br><span class="line">    </span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">location</span> <span class="string">/</span> &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">root</span>   <span class="string">/usr/share/nginx/html;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">index</span>  <span class="string">index.html</span> <span class="string">index.htm;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">try_files</span> <span class="string">$uri</span> <span class="string">$uri/</span> <span class="string">/index.html;</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">location</span> <span class="string">/api</span> &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">proxy_set_header</span>  <span class="string">Host</span> <span class="string">$host;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">proxy_set_header</span>  <span class="string">X-Real-IP</span> <span class="string">$remote_addr;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">proxy_set_header</span>  <span class="string">X-Forwarded-For</span> <span class="string">$proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">proxy_set_header</span>  <span class="string">X-Forwarded-Host</span> <span class="string">$server_name;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">proxy_pass</span>        <span class="string">http://backend:8000;</span></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="string">proxy_redirect</span>    <span class="string">default;</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><blockquote><p><strong>Important:</strong> The .NET CLI and also Visual Studio provide a great set of pre-defined templates that also include React, Angular and more great stuff, which I encourage to give it a try. Also, pretty much of this tutorial can be also take .NET on the frontend, with the help of amazing Blazor 💖✨ </p></blockquote><h2 id="2-Now-it’s-time-for-NET-in-the-x2F-backend-Set-up-Minimal-API-for-MongoDB"><a href="#2-Now-it’s-time-for-NET-in-the-x2F-backend-Set-up-Minimal-API-for-MongoDB" class="headerlink" title="2) Now it’s time for .NET in the &#x2F;backend: Set up Minimal API for MongoDB"></a>2) Now it’s time for .NET in the &#x2F;backend: Set up Minimal API for MongoDB</h2><p>Here things become more interesting. By scaffolding a new Web API from .NET 6, we can implement a very-simple, still small program to call MongoDB collection and support some basic operations for our API, and we can add Swagger+OpenAPI support with a few lines of code:</p><figure class="highlight csharp"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br><span class="line">51</span><br><span class="line">52</span><br><span class="line">53</span><br><span class="line">54</span><br><span class="line">55</span><br><span class="line">56</span><br><span class="line">57</span><br><span class="line">58</span><br><span class="line">59</span><br><span class="line">60</span><br><span class="line">61</span><br><span class="line">62</span><br><span class="line">63</span><br><span class="line">64</span><br><span class="line">65</span><br><span class="line">66</span><br><span class="line">67</span><br><span class="line">68</span><br><span class="line">69</span><br><span class="line">70</span><br><span class="line">71</span><br><span class="line">72</span><br><span class="line">73</span><br><span class="line">74</span><br><span class="line">75</span><br><span class="line">76</span><br><span class="line">77</span><br><span class="line">78</span><br><span class="line">79</span><br><span class="line">80</span><br><span class="line">81</span><br><span class="line">82</span><br><span class="line">83</span><br><span class="line">84</span><br><span class="line">85</span><br><span class="line">86</span><br><span class="line">87</span><br><span class="line">88</span><br><span class="line">89</span><br><span class="line">90</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> System;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> System.Linq;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> System.Threading.Tasks;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> MongoDB.Bson;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> MongoDB.Bson.Serialization.Attributes;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> MongoDB.Driver;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> Models;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">using</span> Swashbuckle.AspNetCore.SwaggerGen;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">var</span> builder = WebApplication.CreateBuilder(args);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="comment">// Learn more about configuring Swagger/OpenAPI at https://aka.ms/aspnetcore/swashbuckle</span></span><br><span class="line">builder.Services.AddEndpointsApiExplorer();</span><br><span class="line">builder.Services.AddSwaggerGen();</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="built_in">string</span> connectionString = builder.Configuration.GetConnectionString(<span class="string">&quot;DocumentDbConnection&quot;</span>);</span><br><span class="line"><span class="built_in">string</span> databaseName = builder.Configuration.GetConnectionString(<span class="string">&quot;DocumentDbName&quot;</span>) ?? <span class="string">&quot;BackendMongoDb&quot;</span>;</span><br><span class="line"><span class="built_in">string</span> collectionName = builder.Configuration.GetConnectionString(<span class="string">&quot;DocumentCollectionName&quot;</span>) ?? <span class="string">&quot;ToDos&quot;</span>;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">builder.Services.AddTransient&lt;MongoClient&gt;((_provider) =&gt; <span class="keyword">new</span> MongoClient(connectionString));</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">var</span> app = builder.Build();</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">var</span> isSwaggerEnabledFromConfig = <span class="built_in">bool</span>.TrueString.Equals(builder.Configuration[<span class="string">&quot;EnableSwagger&quot;</span>] ?? <span class="string">&quot;&quot;</span>, StringComparison.OrdinalIgnoreCase);</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span> (isSwaggerEnabledFromConfig) </span><br><span class="line">&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    Console.WriteLine(<span class="string">&quot;Swagger enabled via appsettings.json&quot;</span>);</span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="comment">// Configure the HTTP request pipeline.</span></span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span> (app.Environment.IsDevelopment() || isSwaggerEnabledFromConfig)</span><br><span class="line">&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    app.UseSwagger();</span><br><span class="line">    app.UseSwaggerUI();</span><br><span class="line">&#125;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">app.MapGet(<span class="string">&quot;/api/todos&quot;</span>, <span class="keyword">async</span> (MongoClient connection) =&gt;</span><br><span class="line">&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="keyword">try</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> database = connection.GetDatabase(databaseName);</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> collection = database.GetCollection&lt;ToDo&gt;(collectionName);</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> results = <span class="keyword">await</span> collection.Find(_ =&gt; <span class="literal">true</span>).ToListAsync().ConfigureAwait(<span class="literal">false</span>);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.Ok(results);</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="keyword">catch</span> (Exception ex)</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.Problem(detail: ex.ToString());</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">&#125;);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">app.MapGet(<span class="string">&quot;/api/todos/&#123;id&#125;&quot;</span>, <span class="keyword">async</span> (<span class="built_in">string</span> id, MongoClient connection) =&gt;</span><br><span class="line">&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="keyword">try</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> database = connection.GetDatabase(databaseName);</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> collection = database.GetCollection&lt;ToDo&gt;(collectionName);</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> result = <span class="keyword">await</span> collection.FindAsync(<span class="keyword">record</span> =&gt; <span class="keyword">record</span>.Id == id).ConfigureAwait(<span class="literal">false</span>) <span class="keyword">as</span> ToDo;</span><br><span class="line">        </span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">if</span> (result <span class="keyword">is</span> <span class="literal">null</span>) </span><br><span class="line">        &#123;</span><br><span class="line">            <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.NotFound();</span><br><span class="line">        &#125;</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.Created(<span class="string">$&quot;/todoitems/<span class="subst">&#123;result.Id&#125;</span>&quot;</span>, result);</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="keyword">catch</span> (Exception ex)</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.Problem(detail: ex.ToString());</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">&#125;);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">app.MapPost(<span class="string">&quot;/api/todos&quot;</span>, <span class="keyword">async</span> (ToDo <span class="keyword">record</span>, <span class="title">MongoClient</span> <span class="title">connection</span>) =&gt;</span><br><span class="line">&#123;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="keyword">try</span></span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> database = connection.GetDatabase(databaseName);</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">var</span> collection = database.GetCollection&lt;ToDo&gt;(collectionName);</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">await</span> collection.InsertOneAsync(<span class="keyword">record</span>).<span class="title">ConfigureAwait</span>(<span class="title">false</span>);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.Created(<span class="string">$&quot;/api/todos/<span class="subst">&#123;<span class="keyword">record</span>.Id&#125;</span>&quot;</span>, <span class="keyword">record</span>);</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="keyword">catch</span> (Exception ex)</span><br><span class="line">    &#123;</span><br><span class="line">        <span class="keyword">return</span> Results.Problem(detail: ex.ToString());</span><br><span class="line">    &#125;</span><br><span class="line">&#125;);</span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">app.Run();</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>Here is a screenshot of the backend when opening the &#x2F;swagger endpoint:</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="400" height="377" src="/2022/06/20/Creating-a-react-app-with-AspNet-Minimal-APIs-and-MongoDb-CosmosDb/swagger.webp" alt="Backend swagger" title="Backend swagger" /><h2 id="3-Oh-Yes-MongoDB-Let’s-Compose-it-and-wrap-up-with-NET"><a href="#3-Oh-Yes-MongoDB-Let’s-Compose-it-and-wrap-up-with-NET" class="headerlink" title="3) Oh! Yes, MongoDB. Let’s Compose it and wrap up with .NET!"></a>3) Oh! Yes, MongoDB. Let’s Compose it and wrap up with .NET!</h2><p>Last but not least, let’s have the Frontend in place, connect it to the Backend and store our To-Dos in MongoDB.</p><p>We can use Compose services here by just grabbing the container images and set things up. </p><figure class="highlight yaml"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br><span class="line">51</span><br><span class="line">52</span><br><span class="line">53</span><br><span class="line">54</span><br><span class="line">55</span><br><span class="line">56</span><br><span class="line">57</span><br><span class="line">58</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line"> <span class="attr">services:</span></span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">frontend:</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">build:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">context:</span> <span class="string">frontend</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">ports:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="number">80</span><span class="string">:80</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">volumes:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">&#x27;.:/app&#x27;</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">&#x27;/app/node_modules&#x27;</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">networks:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">react-frontend</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">depends_on:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">backend</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">links:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">backend</span></span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">backend:</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">build:</span> <span class="string">backend</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">restart:</span> <span class="string">always</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">ports:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="number">8000</span><span class="string">:8000</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">depends_on:</span> </span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">mongo</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">links:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">mongo</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">environment:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">ASPNETCORE_URLS=http://+:8000</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">EnableSwagger=true</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">networks:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">react-backend</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">react-frontend</span></span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">mongo:</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">restart:</span> <span class="string">always</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">image:</span> <span class="string">mongo:4.2.0</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">volumes:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">./data:/data/db</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">networks:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">react-backend</span></span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">mongo-express:</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">image:</span> <span class="string">mongo-express</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">restart:</span> <span class="string">always</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">ports:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="number">8081</span><span class="string">:8081</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">environment:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">ME_CONFIG_MONGODB_ADMINUSERNAME:</span> <span class="string">root</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="attr">ME_CONFIG_MONGODB_ADMINPASSWORD:</span> <span class="string">example</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">depends_on:</span> </span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">mongo</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">links:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">mongo</span></span><br><span class="line">    <span class="attr">networks:</span></span><br><span class="line">      <span class="bullet">-</span> <span class="string">react-backend</span></span><br><span class="line"></span><br><span class="line"><span class="attr">networks:</span></span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">react-backend:</span> &#123;&#125;</span><br><span class="line">  <span class="attr">react-frontend:</span> &#123;&#125; </span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>The compose file also includes a Mongo-Express server in the Compose file so we can quickly explore the NoSQL documents and check everything end-to-end from UI in React either Swagger document generated for us with .NET</p><p>Also, I added a <code>EnableSwagger</code> flag as a Environment variable, which can be read and set accordingly in case you wan to expose Swagger endpoint. To learn more about Appsettings.json, environment variables and overriding them for Docker containers you can follow this link:</p><ul><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/fundamentals/configuration/?view=aspnetcore-6.0#naming-of-environment-variables">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/fundamentals/configuration/?view=aspnetcore-6.0#naming-of-environment-variables</a></li></ul><h2 id="Bonus-tip-CosmosDB-support-out-of-the-box"><a href="#Bonus-tip-CosmosDB-support-out-of-the-box" class="headerlink" title="Bonus tip: CosmosDB support out of the box!"></a>Bonus tip: CosmosDB support out of the box!</h2><p>We can take advantage of using Azure CosmosDB, which supports MongoDB connector so it’s pretty easy to set-up and swap from vanilla MongoDB to use CosmosDB. Here I include some links for reference along with more samples to follow-up:</p><ul><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/mongodb/connect-using-mongoose/">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/mongodb/connect-using-mongoose/</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/mongodb/mongodb-introduction/">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/mongodb/mongodb-introduction/</a></li><li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/cosmosdb/build-a-node-js-app-with-azure-cosmos-dbs-api-for-mongodb/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/cosmosdb/build-a-node-js-app-with-azure-cosmos-dbs-api-for-mongodb/</a></li></ul><p>Happy coding!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">I&#39;ve been using React for while by mixing it up with .NET stuff and enjoying it a lot. For this post, I decided to combine them along with Docker Compose, ASP.NET Minimal APIs and MongoDB support!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="REST" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/REST/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="containers" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/containers/"/>
    
    <category term="Codespaces" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Codespaces/"/>
    
    <category term="Github" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Github/"/>
    
    <category term="React" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/React/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My favorite 10 DEV+Cloud announcements from Microsoft Build 2022</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/</id>
    <published>2022-05-31T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.527Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you missed it, last week was Microsoft Build 2022! Here I share my top 10 favorite DEV+Cloud announcements and links for keeping an eye in 2022.</p><!-- more --><h2 id="About-Microsoft-x2F-x2F-Build-Conference"><a href="#About-Microsoft-x2F-x2F-Build-Conference" class="headerlink" title="About Microsoft &#x2F;&#x2F;Build Conference"></a>About Microsoft &#x2F;&#x2F;Build Conference</h2><p>Microsoft Build Conference it’s one of my favorite developer conferences which I follow from ~2015. Every year, Microsoft traditionally showcases the technologies and products that are coming next during a 1-2 all day event, taking several sessions at the same time in Seattle, remote and around the world. </p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/preview.webp" alt="About Microsoft Build Conference" title="About Microsoft Build Conference" /><p>Featuring cloud, no-code tools, M365, Visual Studio, JavaScript .NET, Artificial Intelligence, SDKs, IoT and also hardware announcements take place for General Availability (GA) and also earlier Private Preview announcements for certain products for customers who are interested in giving them a try and provide feedback. </p><p>Here are I my top 10 DEV+Cloud related announcements:</p><h2 id="1-Azure-Container-Apps-is-now-generally-available"><a href="#1-Azure-Container-Apps-is-now-generally-available" class="headerlink" title="1) Azure Container Apps is now generally available."></a>1) Azure Container Apps is now generally available.</h2><p>Azure Container Apps (ACA) enables customers to run microservices and containerized apps on a serverless platform built on Azure Kubernetes Service and extend with well-known ecosystem projects like KEDA (Kubernetes Event-driven Autoscaling extension), Dapr (Distributed Application Runtime and Envoy.</p><p>Read more: <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/azure-container-apps-general-availability/ba-p/3416885">https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/azure-container-apps-general-availability/ba-p/3416885</a></p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/azure-container-apps.webp" alt="Azure Container Apps" title="Azure Container Apps" /><blockquote><p>More about Azure Container Apps: <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/container-apps/#overview">https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/container-apps/#overview</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="2-GitHub-Copilot-now-Generally-Available"><a href="#2-GitHub-Copilot-now-Generally-Available" class="headerlink" title="2) GitHub Copilot now Generally Available"></a>2) GitHub Copilot now Generally Available</h2><p>GitHub Copilot is a pair programming tool developed by GitHub (Microsoft) with OpenAI tool that enables their users the ability understand context from inputs like comments to suggest lines or code within development environments such as Visual Studio. Also, GitHub Copilot extension is available for IDEs and editors, from Visual Studio Code, JetBrains, Neovim, Visual Studio IDE and also GitHub Codespaces.</p><p>During &#x2F;&#x2F;Build Conference, Microsoft announced that Copilot will be for students, Build 2022 attendees, and verified open-source contributors!</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="400" height="225" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/github-copilot.webp" alt="GitHub Copilot now Generally Available" title="GitHub Copilot now Generally Available" /><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/ai/how-ai-makes-developers-lives-easier-and-helps-everybody-learn-to-develop-software/">https://blogs.microsoft.com/ai/how-ai-makes-developers-lives-easier-and-helps-everybody-learn-to-develop-software/</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="3-TypeScript-4-6-out-and-4-7-beta-announced"><a href="#3-TypeScript-4-6-out-and-4-7-beta-announced" class="headerlink" title="3) TypeScript 4.6 out and 4.7 beta announced."></a>3) TypeScript 4.6 out and 4.7 beta announced.</h2><p>A new version of TypeScript is available and packed with a lot of interesting features out for beta.  You can give it a try to latest version of TypeScript right from <a href="https://www.typescriptlang.org/">https://www.typescriptlang.org/</a> and take a look on latest features listed in Microsoft Blogs link below:</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/typescript-4-7.webp" alt="Typescript 4.7 announced" title="Typescript 4.7 announced" /><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/typescript/announcing-typescript-4-7/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/typescript/announcing-typescript-4-7/</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="4-NET-MAUI-and-Blazor-announcements"><a href="#4-NET-MAUI-and-Blazor-announcements" class="headerlink" title="4) .NET MAUI and Blazor announcements"></a>4) .NET MAUI and Blazor announcements</h2><p>.NET MAUI is out!! 🎉 A single, unified .NET experience for developing applications across mobile and web supporting Mac Catalyst, iOS and Android from one single place. NET MAUI is the next, natural sucesor of Xamarin and now you can incorporate web components developed with Blazor framework by using primarily C# instead of JavaScript. Alternatively, you can use BlazorWebView control for rendering Razor components into an embedded Web View for re-using web UI based components across mobile, desktop and web.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="150" height="85" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/net-maui-robot.webp" alt=".NET MAUI is out" title=".NET MAUI is out" /><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/introducing-dotnet-maui-one-codebase-many-platforms/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/introducing-dotnet-maui-one-codebase-many-platforms/</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="5-Azure-Kubernetes-Service-AKS-updates-amp-cloud-extensions"><a href="#5-Azure-Kubernetes-Service-AKS-updates-amp-cloud-extensions" class="headerlink" title="5) Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS) updates &amp; cloud extensions"></a>5) Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS) updates &amp; cloud extensions</h2><p>For Azure Kubernetes Services (AKS), there are 3 new capabilities enabled for k8s clusters known as Cluster Extensions: Dapr, Azure Machine Learning and GitOps. All of them can be managed from well known tools like the Azure CLI and the Azure SDKs.</p><p>As mentioned <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/dapr-ml-gitops-extensions-ga-on-aks/ba-p/3423296">here</a>, Cluster extensions provide an at-scale mechanism to deploy, update and manage the lifecycle of services represented by extension instances running on your AKS clusters.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="388" height="170" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/aks-extensions-2.webp" alt="AKS updates" title="AKS updates" /><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/azure-kubernetes-service-aks-updates-for-seamless-developer-and/ba-p/3407089">https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/azure-kubernetes-service-aks-updates-for-seamless-developer-and/ba-p/3407089</a></p></blockquote><p>More about Cluster extensions: <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/dapr-ml-gitops-extensions-ga-on-aks/ba-p/3423296">https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/dapr-ml-gitops-extensions-ga-on-aks/ba-p/3423296</a></p><h2 id="6-Azure-Static-Web-Apps-CLI-is-now-GA-global-access"><a href="#6-Azure-Static-Web-Apps-CLI-is-now-GA-global-access" class="headerlink" title="6) Azure Static Web Apps CLI is now GA (global access)"></a>6) Azure Static Web Apps CLI is now GA (global access)</h2><p>Azure Static Web Apps enables you to deploy your full-stack web apps by connecting your Git repository and get a lot of features out of the box, including:</p><ul><li>Web hosting for static content (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and images).</li><li>Integrated API support provided by Azure Functions </li><li>First-class GitHub and Azure DevOps integration </li><li>Globally distributed static content (CDN)</li><li>Free SSL certificates</li><li>Custom domains</li><li>Auth provider integrations with Azure Active Directory, GitHub, and Twitter.</li><li>And more.</li></ul><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="300" height="170" src="/2022/05/31/My-favorite-10-announcements-from-Microsoft-Build-2022/azure-static-web-apps.webp" alt="Azure Static Web Apps" title="Azure Static Web Apps" /><blockquote><p>Recommended reading: <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/app-service/static/">https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/app-service/static/</a></p></blockquote><p>More about <code>az-swa</code> announcement: <a href="https://dev.to/azure/azure-static-web-apps-cli-is-now-ga-global-access-1714">https://dev.to/azure/azure-static-web-apps-cli-is-now-ga-global-access-1714</a></p><h2 id="7-Dev-Box-and-Azure-Deployment-Environments"><a href="#7-Dev-Box-and-Azure-Deployment-Environments" class="headerlink" title="7) Dev Box and Azure Deployment Environments"></a>7) Dev Box and Azure Deployment Environments</h2><p>Microsoft Dev Box is a new Azure cloud service for hybrid development teams that provides developers with secure, ready-to-code developer workstations which are pre-configured for specific stacks and tasks so developers can get to straight to work without having to worry about configuring it.</p><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-developer-community-blog/introducing-microsoft-dev-box/ba-p/3412063">https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-developer-community-blog/introducing-microsoft-dev-box/ba-p/3412063</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="8-Visual-Studio-2022-for-Mac-is-now-available"><a href="#8-Visual-Studio-2022-for-Mac-is-now-available" class="headerlink" title="8) Visual Studio 2022 for Mac is now available!"></a>8) Visual Studio 2022 for Mac is now available!</h2><p>The next version of Visual Studio 2022 for Mac is out! v17.0 it’s available to download which is packed with full native macOS UI support, .NET 6 based and optimized for Apple Silicon (ARM64) processors. Main features include:</p><ul><li>.NET 6, C# 10 and Azure Functions v4 support.</li><li>MAUI tooling support</li><li>Git Changes window</li></ul><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/visualstudio/visual-studio-2022-for-mac-is-now-available/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/visualstudio/visual-studio-2022-for-mac-is-now-available/</a></p></blockquote><p><strong>Release Notes:</strong> <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releases/2022/mac-release-notes-preview#17.3.0-pre.1">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releases/2022/mac-release-notes-preview#17.3.0-pre.1</a></p><h2 id="9-Windows-Terminal-Preview-1-14-Release"><a href="#9-Windows-Terminal-Preview-1-14-Release" class="headerlink" title="9) Windows Terminal Preview 1.14 Release"></a>9) Windows Terminal Preview 1.14 Release</h2><p>The new Windows Terminal release is out, containing a lot of improvements and ability to enable it as default by using the Windows settings app or inside Windows Terminal’s settings. </p><p>Windows Terminal can be installed from the Microsoft Store or from the GitHub releases page. </p><blockquote><p>Read more: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/commandline/windows-terminal-preview-1-14-release/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/commandline/windows-terminal-preview-1-14-release/</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="10-M365-and-Microsoft-Teams-announcements"><a href="#10-M365-and-Microsoft-Teams-announcements" class="headerlink" title="10) M365 and Microsoft Teams announcements"></a>10) M365 and Microsoft Teams announcements</h2><p>Last but not least, several M365 announcements took place around Microsoft Teams, Low-Code &#x2F; No-code, Microsoft Graph. Some key announcements included:</p><ul><li>Teams JS 2.0 SDK - Developer Preview</li><li>Teams Toolkit for Visual Studio Code &amp;  Visual Studio 2022 - Generally Available</li><li>Microsoft Teams app model &amp; Microsoft Graph updates</li><li>Loop components and Adaptive Card-based components</li><li>Microsoft Teams Framework (TeamsFx) - A set of Temas based components incluidng CLI, VS Code extensions and SDKs (NuGet, NPM)</li><li>New Teams Graph API (Create messages, chat, and more)</li></ul><p>Here I share some links for further reading:</p><ul><li><p>Announcing Microsoft Power Pages: Build secure, low-code websites – <a href="https://aka.ms/Build22-Power-Pages-Blog">https://aka.ms/Build22-Power-Pages-Blog</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Teams Monetization for your Apps (In-App Purchases, subscription models) – <a href="http://aka.ms/TeamsMonetization/IAP">http://aka.ms/TeamsMonetization/IAP</a></p></li><li><p>Build collaborative apps with Microsoft Teams – <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/blog/2022/05/24/build-collaborative-apps-with-microsoft-teams/">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/blog/2022/05/24/build-collaborative-apps-with-microsoft-teams/</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Graph @ Build 2022 – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/microsoft-graph-build-2022/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/microsoft-graph-build-2022/</a></p></li><li><p>Introducing Live Share: Interactive app experiences in Microsoft Teams meetings – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/introducing-live-share-interactive-app-experiences-in-microsoft-teams-meetings/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/introducing-live-share-interactive-app-experiences-in-microsoft-teams-meetings/</a></p></li><li><p>What’s new for Office Add-ins at Build 2022 – Microsoft – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/whats-new-for-office-add-ins-at-build-2022/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/whats-new-for-office-add-ins-at-build-2022/</a></p></li><li><p>Increase engagement and discoverability of your data with Microsoft Graph connectors – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/increase-engagement-and-discoverability-of-your-data-with-microsoft-graph-connectors/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/increase-engagement-and-discoverability-of-your-data-with-microsoft-graph-connectors/</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Teams Toolkit for Visual Studio Code now generally available – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/microsoft-teams-toolkit-for-visual-studio-code-now-generally-available/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/microsoft365dev/microsoft-teams-toolkit-for-visual-studio-code-now-generally-available/</a></p></li></ul><h2 id="More-links-for-Build-2022-Announcements"><a href="#More-links-for-Build-2022-Announcements" class="headerlink" title="More links for Build 2022 Announcements"></a>More links for Build 2022 Announcements</h2><ul><li><p>Visual Studio at Microsoft Build 2022 – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/visualstudio/visual-studio-at-microsoft-build-2022/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/visualstudio/visual-studio-at-microsoft-build-2022/</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2022/05/24/at-microsoft-build-microsoft-is-delivering-tools-developers-can-use-today/">https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2022/05/24/at-microsoft-build-microsoft-is-delivering-tools-developers-can-use-today/</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/scale-your-cloudnative-apps-and-accelerate-app-modernization-with-azure-the-best-cloud-for-your-apps/">https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/scale-your-cloudnative-apps-and-accelerate-app-modernization-with-azure-the-best-cloud-for-your-apps/</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Store grows with the developer community – <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsdeveloper/2022/05/24/microsoft-store-grows-with-the-developer-community/">https://blogs.windows.com/windowsdeveloper/2022/05/24/microsoft-store-grows-with-the-developer-community/</a></p></li><li><p>General availability: Azure Cosmos DB Python SDK async IO support – <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/updates/general-availability-azure-cosmos-db-python-sdk-async-io-support/">https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/updates/general-availability-azure-cosmos-db-python-sdk-async-io-support/</a></p></li><li><p>Announcing General Availability for GitOps with Flux v2 in Azure<br><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-arc-blog/announcing-general-availability-for-gitops-with-flux-v2-in-azure/ba-p/3408051">https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-arc-blog/announcing-general-availability-for-gitops-with-flux-v2-in-azure/ba-p/3408051</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft 365 announcements – <a href="https://aka.ms/m365/build22">https://aka.ms/m365/build22</a></p></li><li><p>Announcing landing zone accelerator for Azure Arc-enabled Kubernetes – <a href="https://aka.ms/ArcK8sLZBlog">https://aka.ms/ArcK8sLZBlog</a></p></li></ul><h2 id="Recordings-now-available"><a href="#Recordings-now-available" class="headerlink" title="Recordings now available!"></a>Recordings now available!</h2><p>On-demand videos from <a href="https://build.microsoft.com/">https://build.microsoft.com</a></p><ul><li>Cloud-Native app modernization sessions – <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/events/resources/build-2022/cloudnative-app-modernization?branch=pr-en-us-975">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/events/resources/build-2022/cloudnative-app-modernization?branch=pr-en-us-975</a></li></ul><h2 id="Book-of-News-amp-highlights"><a href="#Book-of-News-amp-highlights" class="headerlink" title="Book of News &amp; highlights"></a>Book of News &amp; highlights</h2><ul><li><p>Build 2022 Book of News: <a href="https://news.microsoft.com/build-2022-book-of-news/">https://news.microsoft.com/build-2022-book-of-news/</a></p></li><li><p>Build 2022 highlights: <a href="https://aka.ms/Build2022highlights">https://aka.ms/Build2022highlights</a></p></li></ul><h2 id="Related-links-and-third-party-announcements"><a href="#Related-links-and-third-party-announcements" class="headerlink" title="Related links and third-party announcements"></a>Related links and third-party announcements</h2><ul><li><p>MacOS Environment Setup For MAUI Development -<br><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/dotnet/2022/05/25/macos-environment-setup-for-maui-development/">https://blog.jetbrains.com/dotnet/2022/05/25/macos-environment-setup-for-maui-development/</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Announces Windows 11, Edge, Teams Updates at Build 2022 – <a href="https://gadgets360.com/laptops/news/microsoft-windows-11-search-store-onenote-edge-teams-pwas-project-volterra-updates-build-2022-3009054">https://gadgets360.com/laptops/news/microsoft-windows-11-search-store-onenote-edge-teams-pwas-project-volterra-updates-build-2022-3009054</a></p></li><li><p>TypeScript 4.7 GA, Visual Studio on Arm64, Azure Deployment Environments, More – <a href="https://visualstudiomagazine.com/articles/2022/05/27/news-roundup.aspx?m=1">https://visualstudiomagazine.com/articles/2022/05/27/news-roundup.aspx?m=1</a></p></li><li><p>Surface at Microsoft Build 2022 – <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/surface-duo/surface-at-microsoft-build-2022/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/surface-duo/surface-at-microsoft-build-2022/</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Introduces Dev Box and Azure Deployment Environments – <a href="https://www.i-programmer.info/news/141-cloud-computing/15454-microsoft-introduces-dev-box-and-azure-deployment-.html">https://www.i-programmer.info/news/141-cloud-computing/15454-microsoft-introduces-dev-box-and-azure-deployment-.html</a></p></li><li><p>10 Takeaways from the Keynote at Microsoft Build 2022 – <a href="https://www.syncfusion.com/blogs/post/10-takeaways-from-the-keynote-at-microsoft-build-2022.aspx">https://www.syncfusion.com/blogs/post/10-takeaways-from-the-keynote-at-microsoft-build-2022.aspx</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft expands Azure OpenAI Service with fine-tuning features and more – <a href="https://techcrunch-com.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/techcrunch.com/2022/05/24/microsoft-expands-azure-openai-service-with-fine-tuning-features-and-more/amp/">https://techcrunch-com.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/techcrunch.com/2022/05/24/microsoft-expands-azure-openai-service-with-fine-tuning-features-and-more/amp/</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft Dev Box is a cloud-powered developer workstation – <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/5/24/23137602/microsoft-dev-box-azure-workstation-cloud-build">https://www.theverge.com/2022/5/24/23137602/microsoft-dev-box-azure-workstation-cloud-build</a></p></li><li><p>.NET MAUI Reaches General Availability, Replacing Xamarin.Forms – <a href="https://visualstudiomagazine.com/articles/2022/05/24/net-maui-ga.aspx">https://visualstudiomagazine.com/articles/2022/05/24/net-maui-ga.aspx</a></p></li><li><p>Visual Studio 2022 for Mac Finally Generally Available – <a href="https://visualstudiomagazine.com/articles/2022/05/25/vs-2022-for-mac-ga.aspx">https://visualstudiomagazine.com/articles/2022/05/25/vs-2022-for-mac-ga.aspx</a></p></li><li><p>Build 2022: GitHub Copilot will be Free for Open Source Contributors &amp; Students This Summer<br>– <a href="https://petri.com/github-copilot-free-open-source-contributors-students-summer/">https://petri.com/github-copilot-free-open-source-contributors-students-summer/</a></p></li><li><p>Introducing F5 NGINX for Azure – Load Balancing Available Natively as a SaaS Offering – <a href="https://www.nginx.com/blog/introducing-f5-nginx-for-azure-load-balancing-available-natively-as-saas-offering-on-microsoft-azure/">https://www.nginx.com/blog/introducing-f5-nginx-for-azure-load-balancing-available-natively-as-saas-offering-on-microsoft-azure/</a></p></li><li><p>Introducing Live Share: Interactive app experiences in Teams meetings – <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/blog/2022/05/24/build-collaborative-apps-with-microsoft-teams/">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/blog/2022/05/24/build-collaborative-apps-with-microsoft-teams/</a></p></li></ul><p>Hope you enjoy it!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">In case you missed it, last week was Microsoft Build 2022! Here I share my top 10 favorite DEV+Cloud announcements and links for keeping an eye in 2022</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="Microsoft" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Microsoft/"/>
    
    <category term="Conferences" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Conferences/"/>
    
    <category term="Kubernetes" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Kubernetes/"/>
    
    <category term="M365" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/M365/"/>
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
    <category term="MAUI" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/MAUI/"/>
    
    <category term=".NET" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/NET/"/>
    
    <category term="Serverless" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Serverless/"/>
    
    <category term="AspNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/AspNet/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Upgrading .NET 5 -&gt; 6 using Minimal APIs, MySQL and GitHub Codespaces</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/03/24/Upgrading-dotnet-5-to-6-using-minimal-apis-and-github-codespaces/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2022/03/24/Upgrading-dotnet-5-to-6-using-minimal-apis-and-github-codespaces/</id>
    <published>2022-03-24T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.555Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>PR #198 merged! Upgrade nginx-aspnet-mysql to net6.0 🚀 Here are the steps I took from moving from .NET 5 API endpoints to Minimal APIs using GitHub Codespaces</p><!-- more --><p>In this post I share some of the steps I took from submitting a PR for <code>docker/awesome-compose</code> repo in GitHub by upgrading code from .NET 5 -&gt; 6, all from the confort of GitHub Codespaces, containers and the .NET tooling!</p><p>GitHub Link: <a href="https://github.com/docker/awesome-compose/pull/198/files">PR #198 on docker&#x2F;awesome-compose</a></p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="300" alt="Upgrading from .NET 5 to .NET 6 using Minimal APIs, MySQL and GitHub Codespaces" src="/2022/03/24/Upgrading-dotnet-5-to-6-using-minimal-apis-and-github-codespaces/preview.png"  title="Upgrading from .NET 5 to .NET 6 using Minimal APIs, MySQL and GitHub Codespaces" /><p>I enjoy working my code with GitHub codespaces. I use the product for blogging and developing my website, general-purpose repositories and most of my .NET samples under my <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/">GitHub profile</a>. Some time ago, I decided to contribute to the <code>awesome-compose</code> repo by adding some .NET code samples which are available <a href="https://github.com/docker/awesome-compose">here</a>.</p><p>The <code>awesome-compose</code> repo is big since it contains a lot of great samples in other languages so definitely I recommend to take a look when learning about Docker-Compose. For scope of this post we will focus on the <code>/nginx-aspnet-mysql</code> folder sapmle which I introduced some time ago by using .NET 5 with basic API endpoints. </p><p>In a nutshell, we will run Docker-compose in the cloud (no need to install Docker-Compose locally, but we can do it if wanted to expand later) with the help of Codespaces in GitHub, develop with .NET 6 and integrate it with a NGINX proxy and MySQL database with classic ADO.NET styled calls. All from the confort our our browser and VS Code online!</p><h2 id="Set-up-a-GitHub-Codespaces-for-developing-on-Awesome-Compose-repository"><a href="#Set-up-a-GitHub-Codespaces-for-developing-on-Awesome-Compose-repository" class="headerlink" title="Set up a GitHub Codespaces for developing on Awesome-Compose repository"></a>Set up a GitHub Codespaces for developing on Awesome-Compose repository</h2><p>You can start a brand new Codespace right away from <a href="https://github.com/codespaces">GitHub Codespaces</a> website. Specifically for .NET 6, you can also build your own codespace with dependencies you need and use .NET 5&#x2F;6&#x2F;X at the same time. For this sample, we can open <code>docker/awesome-compose</code> directly in Codespaces and it will launch with default codespace image (Docker based).</p><p>In order to add support for .NET + Docker-Compose awesomeness, we can add some container sugar by just copy-paste the contents of the <code>.devcontainer</code> folder, which is actually another sample that I made in the past for targeting .NET 6.</p><p><code>git clone https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-minimal-api.git</code></p><p>By doing so, Codespaces may ask you to rebuild your codespace and after it, we can start changes with our <code>Program.cs</code>, <code>.csproj</code> and <code>Dockerfile</code> files.</p><blockquote><p>For this sample, I re-used files from the <code>stvansolano/dotnet6-minimal-api</code> which is based .NET 6.</p></blockquote><p>In case you want to give it a try, you can list the installed SDKs versions of .NET from the Codespace with VS Code Command Prompt:</p><p><code>dotnet --list-sdks</code></p><blockquote><p>Make sure .NET 6 is listed there and you would be ready to build your code.</p></blockquote><p>For creating a new ASP.NET web project:</p><p><code>dotnet new web --name aspnetapp</code></p><h2 id="Running-Docker-Compose-inside-Codespaces"><a href="#Running-Docker-Compose-inside-Codespaces" class="headerlink" title="Running Docker-Compose inside Codespaces"></a>Running Docker-Compose inside Codespaces</h2><p>Once we have our <code>.devcontainer</code> files from previous section, we ca use the command line (CLI) in VS Code, which is supported on the browser by GitHub Codespaces. Finally, make sure to run <code>docker-compose</code> command under the <code>/nginx-aspnet-mysql</code> folder</p><p><code>docker-compose up -d</code></p><p>And that’s it! The code contains a basic sample that contains:</p><ul><li>Nginx based proxy</li><li>ASP.NET Minimal Web API </li><li>Access a MySQL database from raw ADO.NET calls using <code>MySqlConnector</code> NuGet package</li></ul><h2 id="A-recap-of-changes-Moving-from-NET-5-to-v6"><a href="#A-recap-of-changes-Moving-from-NET-5-to-v6" class="headerlink" title="A recap of changes: Moving from .NET 5 to v6"></a>A recap of changes: Moving from .NET 5 to v6</h2><p>If you are migrating from .NET 5 to 6, here is a quick summary of changes to be aware of my <a href="https://github.com/docker/awesome-compose/pull/198/files">PR #198 in awesome-docker repo</a>:</p><ol><li>You need to change the TargetFramework to net6.0 in <code>.csproj</code> file</li><li>You can start to use the implicit usings in the <code>.csproj</code> by adding <code>&lt;ImplicitUsings&gt;enable&lt;/ImplicitUsings&gt;</code> tag</li><li>Move your endpoints up as part of <code>app.MapGet</code> calls in <code>Program.cs</code> file</li><li>Refactor and clean-up the <code>Program.cs</code> file</li><li>Build and fix compilation issues (a few in our sample)</li></ol><p>Also, you may update references if needed, in this case <code>MySqlConnector</code> to latest version available (in this case, MySQL is supported in .NET 6!)</p><p><code>dotnet add package MySqlConnector --version 2.1.2</code></p><p>Happy coding!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">PR #198 merged! Upgrade nginx-aspnet-mysql to net6.0 🚀 Here are the steps I took from moving from .NET 5 API endpoints to Minimal APIs using GitHub Codespaces</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="REST" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/REST/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="containers" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/containers/"/>
    
    <category term="Codespaces" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Codespaces/"/>
    
    <category term="Github" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Github/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Exam passed! Microsoft AI Fundamentals AI-900 Certification</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2021/11/20/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Artificial-Intelligence-Fundamentals-AI-900-certification/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2021/11/20/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Artificial-Intelligence-Fundamentals-AI-900-certification/</id>
    <published>2021-11-20T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.511Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a while since my latest certification in tech but finally get some time to look back and prepare for AI-900: Azure Artificial Intelligence exam which I successfully passed last week!</p><!-- more --><h2 id="About-the-exam-Microsoft-AI-Fundamentals-AI-900-Certification"><a href="#About-the-exam-Microsoft-AI-Fundamentals-AI-900-Certification" class="headerlink" title="About the exam: Microsoft AI Fundamentals AI-900 Certification"></a>About the exam: Microsoft AI Fundamentals AI-900 Certification</h2><p><a href="https://www.credly.com/badges/df96d8bd-e0c1-41d1-a1ba-b3d30e39696f/public_url"><img src="/Exam-passed-Microsoft-Artificial-Intelligence-Fundamentals-AI-900-certification/preview.webp" alt="Microsoft AI Fundamentals AI-900 -Image"></a></p><blockquote><p>Verified by <a href="https://www.credly.com/badges/df96d8bd-e0c1-41d1-a1ba-b3d30e39696f">Credly</a></p></blockquote><p>Earners of the Azure AI Fundamentals certification demonstrates the foundational knowledge of machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) concepts and related Microsoft Azure services. </p><ul><li>Azure Bot Services</li><li>Azure Machine Learning</li><li>Cognitive Services in Azure</li><li>Azure ML Studio</li></ul><h3 id="Skills-measured"><a href="#Skills-measured" class="headerlink" title="Skills measured:"></a>Skills measured:</h3><ul><li>Describe Artificial Intelligence workloads and considerations</li><li>Describe fundamental principles of machine learning on Azure</li><li>Describe features of computer vision workloads on Azure</li><li>Describe features of Natural Language Processing (NLP) workloads on Azure</li><li>Describe features of conversational AI workloads on Azure</li></ul><p><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/ai-900?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/ai-900</a></p><h2 id="My-experience-taking-exams-online-through-Microsoft-Learning"><a href="#My-experience-taking-exams-online-through-Microsoft-Learning" class="headerlink" title="My experience taking exams online through Microsoft Learning"></a>My experience taking exams online through Microsoft Learning</h2><p>This was the first time scheduling exam from home under the Microsoft Learning experience, which makes a ton easier to take the exam over the PearsonVUE exam provider and take the test. My previous certifications were on-site with PearsonVUE but I really liked the all-remote experience this time. Here are some steps I took along the way:</p><ol><li><p>From <a href="https://microsoft.com/mcp">https://microsoft.com/mcp</a> you can explore your certifications Dashboard, pick an exam of your choice, and your language. I prefer taking the exams on English to avoid translation terminology that can be distracting sometimes.</p></li><li><p>Schedule the exam, prepare your space and computer settings from PearsonVUE indications (both email and online indications are enough)</p></li><li><p>On exam-day, prepare your space</p></li></ol><ul><li>You will be recorded all the time and monitored by proctor</li><li>Avoid people around to interrupt your exam</li><li>Don’t use headsets. If possible, keep your basics on laptop&#x2F;camera&#x2F;mic for speeding up check-in process as you may need to move them to be screened and be OK for the exam</li><li>Keep your desk small, clean and remove as much clutter as you can</li><li>You can only use one monitor and minimum complimentary hardware.</li></ul><blockquote><p><strong>Exam vouchers:</strong> I strongly recommend you to keep an eye on Microsoft events and Challenges since they provide free-vouchers.</p></blockquote><h2 id="Recommended-resources-for-exam"><a href="#Recommended-resources-for-exam" class="headerlink" title="Recommended resources for exam"></a>Recommended resources for exam</h2><p>If you want to prepare or considering to take the exam, I definitely recommend to a look and browse the amazing Microsoft Docs materials for preparing to exam, which at the time of writing this post includes:</p><ul><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/paths/get-started-with-artificial-intelligence-on-azure/?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">Microsoft Azure AI Fundamentals: Get started with artificial intelligence</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/paths/create-no-code-predictive-models-azure-machine-learning/?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">Microsoft Azure AI Fundamentals: Explore visual tools for machine learning</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/paths/explore-computer-vision-microsoft-azure/?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">Microsoft Azure AI Fundamentals: Explore computer vision</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/paths/explore-natural-language-processing/?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">Microsoft Azure AI Fundamentals: Explore natural language processing</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/paths/explore-conversational-ai/?WT.mc_id=stvansolano">Microsoft Azure AI Fundamentals: Explore conversational AI</a></li></ul><p>See the full list and additional content at: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/ai-900">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/ai-900</a></p><h2 id="On-exam-day-Be-ready"><a href="#On-exam-day-Be-ready" class="headerlink" title="On exam-day: Be ready!"></a>On exam-day: Be ready!</h2><p>For more on preparing for the exam day, I recommend to check the exam provider (PearsonVue) website for getting ready for exam: <a href="https://home.pearsonvue.com/onvue/system-requirements">https://home.pearsonvue.com/onvue/system-requirements</a></p><p>I would be more than happy to connect in case you want to get more tips for getting ready for the exam. Please feel free to reach out to my <a href="http://cr.linkedin.com/in/stvansolano">LinkedIn here</a></p><p>-Esteban</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Microsoft Certified: Azure AI Fundamentals was issued to Esteban Solano Granados</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="AI" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/AI/"/>
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
    <category term="Exam" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Exam/"/>
    
    <category term="Certification" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Certification/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Playing with .NET 6 preview, C# 10 and Docker</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2021/08/02/Playing-with-NET-6-preview-csharp10-docker-containers/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2021/08/02/Playing-with-NET-6-preview-csharp10-docker-containers/</id>
    <published>2021-08-02T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.531Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>.NET 6 is coming on November 2021! Here are some and some interesting links to keep an eye on from recent announcements from Microsot Build 2021 Conference. A lot of great stuff coming up!</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Long-time-no-blogging"><a href="#Long-time-no-blogging" class="headerlink" title="Long time, no blogging!"></a>Long time, no blogging!</h2><p>It has been a while from last time I blogged. I’m really having a great time and fun since I joined Microsoft to work remotely, and it’s always great to take some time back on my notes to share some cool tech with the community. This time, .NET 6 stuff!</p><blockquote><p>ICYMI: Here is the link to my previous post on joining Microsoft: <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/2020/12/07/Work-at-an-awesome-place-I-am-joining-Microsoft/">2020&#x2F;12&#x2F;07&#x2F;Work at an awesome place. I’m joining Microsoft!</a></p></blockquote><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2021/08/02/Playing-with-NET-6-preview-csharp10-docker-containers/preview.webp" alt="Play with dotnet 6 and docker" title="Play with dotnet 6 and docker" /><h2 id="Let’s-get-started"><a href="#Let’s-get-started" class="headerlink" title="Let’s get started."></a>Let’s get started.</h2><p>Here is a summary of what’s coming with .NET 6 tooling:</p><ul><li>C# 10 preview features</li><li>Minimal APIs support</li><li>Linq &amp; EF Core 6 previews</li><li>.NET MAUI</li><li>And more to come</li></ul><p>At the time of publishing this post, there are 6 official previews released of .NET 6 (with Preview 7 going out soon!). The good thing is that tooling is going pretty much the same across those (VS Code support, dotnet build, run, etc) while Hot Reload is coming across .NET and Visual Studio 2022 on 64bit is now on Preview!</p><p>If you want to give it a try, I took some time to put it altogether in a new GitHub repo, which can be used with GitHub Codespaces and Docker so you don’t have to install locally in your machine! </p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/">https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/</a></p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview"><img src="/2021/08/02/Playing-with-NET-6-preview-csharp10-docker-containers/dotnet6-preview-repo.png" alt="NET 6 preview repo link -Image"></a></p><p>There are two ways for using the repo:</p><ol><li><strong>GitHub Codespaces</strong>: If you have GitHub account with Codespaces support (public preview available, going GA soon!), you can just open it from “Code” button, then &gt; “Open with Codespaces”. <strong>Tip:</strong> You can use the repo as a template for creating your own repo!</li><li>** Fork&#x2F;clone locally**: You can use VSCode with the repo and install the <em>Visual Studio Code Remote Development</em> extension, Docker and open the folder in container.</li></ol><p>More details: <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/remote/containers">Visual Studio Code Remote Development</a></p><blockquote><p>By opening from GitHub either VS Code (latest version preferarly) you would be ready to go!</p></blockquote><h2 id="Project-structure-amp-samples"><a href="#Project-structure-amp-samples" class="headerlink" title="Project structure &amp; samples"></a>Project structure &amp; samples</h2><ul><li>&#x2F;ConsoleApp (Minimal Console app with C# 10 &#x2F; .NET 6 support)</li><li>&#x2F;ConsoleApp.EntityFramework (.NET 6 + EF with SQLite)</li><li>&#x2F;ConsoleApp.Linq (Some new LINQ coming features, no EF)</li><li>&#x2F;WebApi (Minimal Web API with C# 9 &#x2F; .NET 6)</li><li>&#x2F;WebApi-Swagger (Minimal Web API with swagger support)</li><li><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/blob/main/src/ci.Dockerfile">CI Dockerfile</a> (yes! We have NuGet support and Docker SDK and Runtime images available!)</li><li><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/blob/main/.github/workflows/dotnet6-docker-build.yml">GitHub Actions with .NET 6</a></li></ul><h2 id="Creating-a-new-Minimal-Web-API"><a href="#Creating-a-new-Minimal-Web-API" class="headerlink" title="Creating a new Minimal Web API"></a>Creating a new Minimal Web API</h2><p><code>dotnet new web -o src/WebApi</code></p><p>Here is how the Program.cs file looks like:</p><pre id="minimal-web-api"></pre><script>  var url = 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/main/src/WebApi/Program.cs';  fetch(url)  .then(res => res.text())  .then((out) => {    document.getElementById("minimal-web-api").innerText = out  })  .catch(err => { throw err });</script><p>Then Run it</p><p><code>dotnet run --project WebApi/WebApi.csproj</code></p><blockquote><p>Important: If you are running it from GitHub Codespace, make sure you have dotnet in your $PATH</p></blockquote><p><code>export DOTNET_ROOT=$HOME/dotnet \     &amp;&amp; export PATH=$PATH:$HOME/dotnet</code></p><h2 id="C-10-Global-usings"><a href="#C-10-Global-usings" class="headerlink" title="C# 10 Global usings"></a>C# 10 Global usings</h2><p>With C# 10 you can place usings into a separate file (e.g Usings.cs) and keep the compiler happy across your clases. Event better, duplicated using statements can be removed and put them in 1 single file:</p><pre id="global-usings"></pre><script>  var url = 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/main/src/WebApi-Swagger/Usings.cs';  fetch(url)  .then(res => res.text())  .then((out) => {    document.getElementById("global-usings").innerText = out  })  .catch(err => { throw err });</script><h2 id="Getting-some-hands-on-GitHub-Actions-NET-6"><a href="#Getting-some-hands-on-GitHub-Actions-NET-6" class="headerlink" title="Getting some hands on GitHub Actions .NET 6"></a>Getting some hands on GitHub Actions .NET 6</h2><p>You can take advantage of the .NET 6 preview builds and use them as Docker images from Docker Hub. Both SDK and Runtime can be used accordingly:</p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/blob/main/.github/workflows/dotnet6-docker-build.yml">https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/blob/main/.github/workflows/dotnet6-docker-build.yml</a></p><pre id="github-action-1"></pre><script>  var url = 'https://raw.githubusercontent.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/main/src/ci.Dockerfile';  fetch(url)  .then(res => res.text())  .then((out) => {    document.getElementById("github-action-1").innerText = out  })  .catch(err => { throw err });</script><h2 id="Running-the-GitHub-action"><a href="#Running-the-GitHub-action" class="headerlink" title="Running the GitHub action"></a>Running the GitHub action</h2><p>Make sure to put it under &#x2F;.github&#x2F;workflows folder so it can be executed automatically on every push on the repo. </p><p>Here is my <code>dotnet6-docker-build.yml</code> file output:</p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview/actions/workflows/dotnet6-docker-build.yml"><img src="/2021/08/02/Playing-with-NET-6-preview-csharp10-docker-containers/github-action-1.png" alt="GitHub action -Image"></a></p><h3 id="NET-6-Preview-blogs"><a href="#NET-6-Preview-blogs" class="headerlink" title=".NET 6 Preview blogs:"></a>.NET 6 Preview blogs:</h3><ul><li>Preview 7: (Coming soon)</li><li>Preview 6: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-6/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-6/</a></li><li>Preview 5: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-5/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-5/</a></li><li>Preview 4: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-4/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-4/</a></li><li>Preview 3: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-3/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-6-preview-3/</a></li><li>EF Core 6 preview: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-entity-framework-core-6-0-preview-5-compiled-models/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-entity-framework-core-6-0-preview-5-compiled-models/</a></li><li>.NET MAUI: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-maui-preview-5/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-maui-preview-5/</a></li><li>ASP.NET 6 preview: <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/aspnet/asp-net-core-updates-in-net-6-preview-5/">https://devblogs.microsoft.com/aspnet/asp-net-core-updates-in-net-6-preview-5/</a></li></ul><h3 id="More-C-awesome-links"><a href="#More-C-awesome-links" class="headerlink" title="More C# awesome links"></a>More C# awesome links</h3><ul><li>C# 10 what’s new: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/whats-new/csharp-10">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/whats-new/csharp-10</a></li><li>C# 9 &amp; preview: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/whats-new/csharp-9">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/whats-new/csharp-9</a></li><li>C# guide: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/</a></li><li>C# Language Versioning: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/language-reference/configure-language-version">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/language-reference/configure-language-version</a></li></ul><p>Don’t forget to open issues in the <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet6-preview">stvansolano&#x2F;dotnet6-preview repo</a> in case something may need ny attention, and if you like it, give it a star. Happy coding! </p><p>P.D: I would be making progress and introduce changes in the repo as new previews got out. So stay refreshing&#x2F;F5-ing! </p><p>-Esteban</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">.NET 6 is coming on November 2021! Here are some and some interesting links to keep an eye on from recent announcements from Microsot Build 2021 Conference. A lot of great stuff coming up!</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Work at an awesome place. I&#39;m joining Microsoft!</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/12/07/Work-at-an-awesome-place-I-am-joining-Microsoft/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/12/07/Work-at-an-awesome-place-I-am-joining-Microsoft/</id>
    <published>2020-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.559Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi colleagues &amp; community! I’m thrilled to announce that I’ve accepted a full-time role to work as part of the Software Engineering Team at Microsoft!</p><!-- more --><p> Yes! 100% remote from Costa Rica. Since working remotely has entering a new era, and given the recent positions opened at Microsoft for Latam I’ve decided it’s a good time to step into a new adventure in my career. </p><p>We know that <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/quarantine-work-is-not-remote-work">Quarantine work is not Remote work</a> and it’s definitely different from what we had and some years ago. Fortunately, Microsoft is doing that pretty well and considering that <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/9/21508964/microsoft-remote-work-from-home-covid-19-coronavirus">they are allowing peeps to work from home -The Verge-</a> during this 2020 hard times and <a href="https://nypost-com.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/nypost.com/2020/10/09/microsoft-will-soon-allow-employees-to-stay-remote-permanently/amp/">they will allow staying remote permanently -NY Post-</a>, so that’s something that called my attention as the right fit happened given my experience and skills.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="500" height="139" src="/2020/12/07/Work-at-an-awesome-place-I-am-joining-Microsoft/microsoft.png" alt="Joining Microsoft" title="Joining Microsoft" /><blockquote><p>If you are interested to join Microsoft, I would recommend to check out the jobs website at Microsoft: <a href="https://careers.microsoft.com/us/en">https://careers.microsoft.com/us/en</a> </p></blockquote><h2 id="Wait-switching-back-from-contracting-services-to-company-lane"><a href="#Wait-switching-back-from-contracting-services-to-company-lane" class="headerlink" title="Wait, switching-back from contracting services to company lane?"></a>Wait, switching-back from contracting services to company lane?</h2><p>I think that’s becoming more frequent  during these times and personally isn’t a one-way trip. More than that, it’s a great chance to bring some learnings and experience from companies I worked with and customers and companies to accomplish Microsoft’s mission: to empower every person and every organization on the planet to achieve more. </p><p>Not a casualty, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/lists/worlds-best-employers">Microsoft ranks within the Top 5 world’s best employers</a> and <a href="https://hbr-org.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/hbr.org/amp/2018/02/people-want-3-things-from-work-but-most-companies-are-built-around-only-one">I discovered this is an opportunity that really fills the 3 things employees generally are looking for: Career, Community, and Cause</a>. Interestingly, those were the 3 factors were that really put me in the contractor&#x2F;freelance role years back. </p><p>During the last years, several distinguished engineers and non-traditional Microsoft guys like Miguel de Icaza (Xamarin), Brendan Burns (Kubernetes), and Guido van Rossum (creator of Python) have joined the company as they keep doing what they love and create amazing cross-platform, open-source and cloud-provided products and tools for allowing others to achieve more. So it’s quite amazing times coming ahead!</p><h2 id="Last-but-not-least-To-all-my-fellow-MVPs-CPM-community-colleagues-course-students-and-MSFT-employees-that-supported-me-during-this-time"><a href="#Last-but-not-least-To-all-my-fellow-MVPs-CPM-community-colleagues-course-students-and-MSFT-employees-that-supported-me-during-this-time" class="headerlink" title="Last but not least: To all my fellow MVPs, CPM, community colleagues, course-students, and MSFT employees that supported me during this time:"></a>Last but not least: To all my fellow MVPs, CPM, community colleagues, course-students, and MSFT employees that supported me during this time:</h2><h2 id="Thank-you"><a href="#Thank-you" class="headerlink" title="Thank you!"></a>Thank you!</h2><p>During my previous time as I worked previously as Software Engineer, trainer and leading community user groups and running events, Microsoft and the .NET Community has been a huge part of my professional journey, which has been an awesome time recognized as part of the MVP Program and allowing me to be in touch with amazing people including Marketing, PMs, Architects and of course developers &amp; students around the globe. I would like to those who were willing to help and support during the pre-COVID times through communities, in-person events, meetups, workshops at universities, and people who supported me and help me by sharing knowledge and attending sessions that I organize together with you. </p><p>I would like to thank everyone who helped me along the way in the past through communities, invitations to face-to-face events, hosting my talks, workshops at universities, and people who supported and helped me by sharing knowledge, attending sessions that we organized together, connections inside and outside the MVP program that encouraged me to learn, travel and contribute with my experiences. </p><p>Now, let me share it in Spanish for the rest of this post:</p><h1 id="En-espanol"><a href="#En-espanol" class="headerlink" title="En español"></a>En español</h1><p>¡Hola colegas y comunidad! ¡Me complace anunciar que acepté una posición a completo para trabajar como parte del equipo de Ingeniería de software en Microsoft!</p><p>¡Sí! 100% remoto. Desde que trabajar de forma remota ha entrado en una nueva era, y dado los puestos recientes abiertos en Microsoft para Latam, he decidido que es un buen momento para dar un paso hacia una nueva aventura en mi carrera.</p><p>Sabemos que <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/quarantine-work-is-not-remote-work">el trabajo en cuarentena no es un trabajo remoto</a> y definitivamente es diferente de lo que teníamos hace algunos años para los que teníamos chance de trabajar remotamente. Afortunadamente, Microsoft lo está haciendo bastante bien y teniendo en cuenta que <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/9/21508964/microsoft-remote-work-from-home-covid-19-coronavirus">están permitiendo que todos trabajen desde casa</a> durante estos tiempos difíciles de 2020 y <a href="https://nypost-com.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/nypost.com/2020/10/09/microsoft-will-soon-allow-employees-to-stay-remote-permanently/amp/">van a permitir permanecer alejados de forma permanente</a>, así que eso es algo que me llamó la atención como acertado el ajuste sucedió dada mi experiencia y habilidades.</p><p>¿Pensando en unirte a Microsoft?</p><blockquote><p>Si estás interesado en unirse a Microsoft, te recomiendo que visites el sitio web de empleos en Microsoft: <a href="https://careers.microsoft.com/us/en">https://careers.microsoft.com/us/en</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="Espera-¿vuelvo-de-la-contratacion-de-servicios-al-mundo-de-trabajo-en-empresa"><a href="#Espera-¿vuelvo-de-la-contratacion-de-servicios-al-mundo-de-trabajo-en-empresa" class="headerlink" title="Espera, ¿vuelvo de la contratación de servicios al mundo de trabajo en empresa?"></a>Espera, ¿vuelvo de la contratación de servicios al mundo de trabajo en empresa?</h2><p>Creo que esto está volviendo más frecuente durante estos tiempos y, personalmente, considero que no es un viaje de ida. Más que eso, es una gran oportunidad para aportar algunos aprendizajes y experiencias de las empresas con las que trabajé y de los clientes y empresas para lograr la misión de Microsoft: empoderar a todas las personas y organizaciones del planeta para que logren más.</p><p>No es una casualidad, Microsoft se encuentra entre los 5 mejores empleadores del mundo y <a href="https://hbr-org.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/hbr.org/amp/2018/02/people-want-3-things-from-work-but-most-companies-are-built-around-only-one">descubrí que esta es una oportunidad que realmente llena las 3 cosas que los empleados generalmente buscan: carrera, comunidad y causa</a>. Curiosamente, esos fueron los 3 factores que realmente me pusieron en el rol de contratista &#x2F; autónomo años atrás.</p><p>Durante los últimos años, varios ingenieros distinguidos y chicos “no tradicionales” del mundo Microsoft como Miguel de Icaza (Xamarin), Brendan Burns (Kubernetes) y Guido van Rossum (creador de Python) se han unido a la empresa mientras siguen haciendo lo que aman y crean. increíbles productos y herramientas multiplataforma, de código abierto y proporcionados en la nube para permitir que otros logren más. ¡Así que se avecinan tiempos asombrosos!</p><h2 id="Por-ultimo-pero-no-menos-importante-A-todos-mis-companeros-MVP-CPM-colegas-de-la-comunidad-estudiantes-de-cursos-y-empleados-de-MSFT-que-me-apoyaron-durante-este-tiempo"><a href="#Por-ultimo-pero-no-menos-importante-A-todos-mis-companeros-MVP-CPM-colegas-de-la-comunidad-estudiantes-de-cursos-y-empleados-de-MSFT-que-me-apoyaron-durante-este-tiempo" class="headerlink" title="Por último, pero no menos importante: A todos mis compañeros MVP, CPM, colegas de la comunidad, estudiantes de cursos y empleados de MSFT que me apoyaron durante este tiempo:"></a>Por último, pero no menos importante: A todos mis compañeros MVP, CPM, colegas de la comunidad, estudiantes de cursos y empleados de MSFT que me apoyaron durante este tiempo:</h2><h2 id="¡Gracias"><a href="#¡Gracias" class="headerlink" title="¡Gracias!"></a>¡Gracias!</h2><p>Durante mi tiempo anterior como ingeniero de software, capacitador y líder en grupos de usuarios de la comunidad y eventos en ejecución, Microsoft y la comunidad .NET han sido una gran parte de mi viaje profesional, que ha sido un tiempo increíble reconocido como parte del programa MVP de Microsoft y me permitió estar en contacto con personas increíbles, incluidos gente de marketing, PMs, arquitectos y, por supuesto, desarrolladores y estudiantes de todo el mundo. </p><p>Me gustaría agradecer a todos los que me echaron una mano en el camino en el pasado a través de comunidades, invitaciones a eventos presenciales, hospedar mis charlas, talleres en universidades, y personas que me apoyaron y me ayudaron compartiendo conocimientos y asistiendo a sesiones que organizamos juntos, conexiones dentro y fuera del programa MVP que me impulsaron a aprender, viajar y contribuir con mis experiencias.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">I&#39;m thrilled to announce that I&#39;ve accepted a full-time role to work as part of the Software Engineering Team at Microsoft</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Microsoft" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Microsoft/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="Career" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Career/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Primer vistazo a .Net Maui (con codigo incluido)</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/</id>
    <published>2020-12-03T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.531Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Demos un vistazo preliminar a .NET Maui previo a los primeros previews que estarán disponibles a la comunidad próximamente! Código y baterías incluídas!</p><!-- more --><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/preview.webp" alt="Maui overview" title="Maui overview" /><p>Esta publicación forma parte del 2do Calendario de Adviento Xamarin, organizado por mi colega Luis Beltran. Te invito a leer las demás publicaciones desde el siguiente link:</p><blockquote><p>Calendario de Adviento Xamarin 2020: <a href="https://www.luisbeltran.mx/2020/11/16/segundo-calendario-de-adviento-de-xamarin-en-espanol/">https://www.luisbeltran.mx/2020/11/16/segundo-calendario-de-adviento-de-xamarin-en-espanol/</a></p></blockquote><h2 id="Sobre-NET-Maui"><a href="#Sobre-NET-Maui" class="headerlink" title="Sobre .NET Maui"></a>Sobre .NET Maui</h2><ul><li>Maui es la evolución natural de Xamarin.Forms, irá tomando forma en 2021 y se espera que los primeros builds y previews se den finales de este año 2020 - principios de 2021 para tomar fuerza en la ola de .NET 6 (vNext).</li><li>La última versión liberada de Xamarin.Forms es la numero 5.0 la cual está saliendo por estos tiempos y su sucesor natural será .NET Maui (No un XF 6 sino -&gt; Maui 1.0). </li><li>Si bien habrá que esperar bastante hasta Noviembre 2021, habrán previews durante casi todo el año de Maui y se espera que alcance la versión .NET 6 la cual será a su vez LTS (Long-Term-Support) lo cual traerá mucha estabilidad en el mediano plazo para los proyectos que estén haciendo la transición a Maui o nazcan completamente bajo esta plataforma.</li></ul><p>Ansioso por .NET MAUI? No puedes esperar? Bueno, por acá algunas sugerencias:</p><ul><li>Prepara tu código para que sea re-utilizable con .NET 5 o .NET Standard</li><li>Revisa constantemente el roadmap de Maui desde su repositorio en GitHub. Actualmente se está preparando lo que podrá ser la preview antes de final de año! <a href="https://github.com/dotnet/maui/wiki/Roadmap#net-maui-preview-1-late-2020">Roadmap 2020-21</a></li><li>Juega con .NET Maui y corre la voz! (es lo que haremos a continuación)</li></ul><h2 id="¿Que-veremos-en-este-articulo"><a href="#¿Que-veremos-en-este-articulo" class="headerlink" title="¿Qué veremos en este artículo?"></a>¿Qué veremos en este artículo?</h2><ul><li>Lo que veremos en esta publicación es meramente experimental. El uso del codigo es con fines exploratorios y no se recomienda utilizarlo para fines de producción.</li><li>Mas que abarcar contenido enfocado en el repositorio, este artículo pretende motivar y e ir conociendo la estructura del proyecto Maui, y servir de guia para que otros desarrolladores den sus primeros pasos en el proyecto y realicen contribuciones alineadas al proyecto.</li><li>Es esperable que muchos principios recopilados  en este artículo se mantengan con el tiempo y sean la base de Maui con lo que la comunidad Xamarin y Microsoft aporten en el proyecto. No obstante, otros pueden cambiar radicalmente y combinarse&#x2F;emigrar en otros proyectos experimentales, software libre y contribuciones OSS de Microsoft.</li></ul><h3 id="Aviso-x2F-Disclaimer-Experimental"><a href="#Aviso-x2F-Disclaimer-Experimental" class="headerlink" title="Aviso &#x2F; Disclaimer [Experimental]"></a>Aviso &#x2F; Disclaimer [Experimental]</h3><ul><li>Varias de las conclusiones e ideas expuestas en este articulo fueron producto de la observación y experimentación con el codigo y pueden (o no) estar alineadas con el roadmap actual Maui al momento de la lectura del artículo o incluso quedarse atrás en el tiempo en lo que Maui toma madurez y estén disponibles las primeras vistas previas en 2021 como previews usando .NET 5 y .NET 6. Por tanto, las opiniones y observaciones en este artículo son propias del autor y pueden no estar alineadas completamente con el roadmap de Microsoft en Maui, lo que estara sujeto a validación y correcciones si el artículo lo amerite. Sólo el tiempo lo dira :) </li><li>Dado que el proyecto sigue aun en desarrollo, no hay garantía de que todo lo escrito en este artículo se mantenga vigente con el tiempo, por lo que puede haber discrepancias y el artículo estara sujeto a correcciones para garantizar la verdad. </li><li>Este artículo NO busca generar discrepancias o faltas a la verdad de lo grandioso que se espera que sea Maui, ni hacer comparaciones con otros frameworks o librerias existentes dentro y fuera de Microsoft.</li></ul><p>Teniendo claro lo anterior, comenzamos :)</p><h2 id="1-Comenzando-con-el-repositorio-de-Maui"><a href="#1-Comenzando-con-el-repositorio-de-Maui" class="headerlink" title="1- Comenzando con el repositorio de Maui."></a>1- Comenzando con el repositorio de Maui.</h2><p>Puedes hacer ‘fork’ o clonar localmente en tu equipo el repositorio de Maui directamente desde GitHub, extenderlo y enviar sugerencias en el codigo. Te recomiendo darle una leida al README.md y el código de conducta que Xamarin ha mantenido desde que es Open Source años atrás:</p><p><a href="https://github.com/dotnet/maui">https://github.com/dotnet/maui</a></p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="585" height="380" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/maui-structure.webp" alt="Maui structure" title="Maui structure" /><h2 id="2-Creando-un-repositorio-tipo-“Playground”-para-Maui"><a href="#2-Creando-un-repositorio-tipo-“Playground”-para-Maui" class="headerlink" title="2- Creando un repositorio tipo “Playground” para Maui"></a>2- Creando un repositorio tipo “Playground” para Maui</h2><p>Para efectos de este ejemplo - disponible en GitHub <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet-maui-playground">bajo mi cuenta</a>, haremos una app Xamarin desde 0 utilizando NetStandard2.0 y los templates de Visual Studio 2019 para Mac y Windows disponibles en 2020, los cuales generan la misma estructura de archivos independientemente de que uses Windows o Mac.</p><p><strong>IMPORTANTE:</strong> El código de Maui actual contiene una carpeta <code>Samples</code> donde de hecho ya viene algo que podemos utilizar si no queremos utilizar este playground. </p><blockquote><p>He puesto el código utilizado en GitHub donde se pueden examinar más de cerca los cambios entre una app Xamarin.Forms de 2020 hacia un .NET Maui experimental.</p></blockquote><p>Por ahora y por la estructura tradicional que estamos usando y como veremos mas adelante con Maui, los proyectos se mantienen compatibles dado que aun son basados en .Net Standard.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="200" height="100" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/hello-world-1.webp" alt="Hello World" title="Hello World" /><blockquote><p>File -&gt; New Project -&gt; Blank Forms App<br><em>Nombre:</em> HelloWorld </p></blockquote><p><strong>¿Qué esperar de esto a futuro en Maui?</strong> Bastante en este aspecto:</p><ul><li>A futuro podremos contar con la característica llamada “Estructura unificada de proyecto” para que podamos apuntar a iOS  Android y correr desde un solo lugar. </li><li>Por lo que veremos más adelante, será cuestión de que en su momento el equipo de Xamarin &#x2F; Microsoft introduzca la nueva generación (o equivalente técnico) para que los proyectos de Android &#x2F; iOS puedan vivir dentro de un proyecto de .NET moderno (5 y superior) con nuevos targets <code>net-android</code> y <code>net-ios</code> para poderse usar a como se hace hoy día con <code>&lt;TargetFrameworks&gt;</code> en los archivos <code>.csproj</code>.</li><li>Dado que .NET 5 tiene desde hace bastante tiempo, podremos esperar que .NET Maui incluya la habilidad de generar y correr los proyectos multi-plataforma desde la mismísima terminal&#x2F;línea de comandos.</li></ul><p>En otras palabras, podremos tener algo como lo siguiente:</p><p><code>dotnet new maui</code></p><p>Lo cual es algo muy común en frameworks como React Native y Flutter hoy en día.</p><h2 id="3-Haciendo-“switch”-a-Maui-en-lugar-de-Xamarin-Forms-para-nuestro-proyecto-experimental"><a href="#3-Haciendo-“switch”-a-Maui-en-lugar-de-Xamarin-Forms-para-nuestro-proyecto-experimental" class="headerlink" title="3- Haciendo “switch” a Maui en lugar de Xamarin.Forms para nuestro proyecto experimental."></a>3- Haciendo “switch” a Maui en lugar de Xamarin.Forms para nuestro proyecto experimental.</h2><p>Desde nuestro app de HelloWorld (playground), agregamos a la solución los proyectos principales que provienen del proyecto Maui, para poderlos compilar y usarlos en nuestra aplicación.</p><p>Para ello simplemente agregamos mediante clic derecho a la solución -&gt; <strong>Add existing project…</strong> y agregamos los siguientes, entre otros:</p><ul><li>Xamarin.Forms.Core</li><li>Xamarin.Forms.Xaml</li><li>Xamarin.Forms.Platform.Android</li><li>Xamarin.Forms.Platform.iOS</li><li>Xamarin.Platform.Handlers (nuevo!)</li></ul><p>Teniendo compilado todo, podemos comentar&#x2F;quitar las referencias de Xamarin.Forms de nuestros proyectos iOS&#x2F;Android para empezar a usar Maui por primera vez!</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="758" height="236" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/hello-world-2-1.webp" alt="Maui references" title="Maui references" /><blockquote><p>Como es esperado, Maui se compone mayormente del codigo original de Xamarin.Forms, con estructura un poco diferente y con codigo nuevo que se espera para la nueva implementación.</p></blockquote><p><strong>¿Qué esperar de esto a futuro en Maui?</strong> Habrá un cambio de nombre en los namespaces como ya se ha anunciado: </p><ul><li><code>System.Maui</code> sustituirá al conocido <code>Xamarin.Forms</code></li><li><code>System.Device</code> sustuirá al conocido <code>Xamarin.Essentials</code></li></ul><h3 id="Probando-IView-y-los-nuevos-Handlers-aka-la-“extincion-de-los-Renderers”"><a href="#Probando-IView-y-los-nuevos-Handlers-aka-la-“extincion-de-los-Renderers”" class="headerlink" title="Probando IView y los nuevos Handlers (aka la “extinción de los Renderers”)"></a>Probando <code>IView</code> y los nuevos <code>Handlers</code> (aka la “extinción de los Renderers”)</h3><p>Maui introducirá mediante los clásicos <code>interfaces</code> de C# una forma mucho más fácil de poder extender e implementar lo que se solía hacer con los famosos <code>Renderers</code> de Xamarin.Forms: Acceder a los controles nativos de una forma directa, sin intermediarios. </p><p>Una de las interfaces se llama <code>IView</code> y al parecer tendremos una para <code>IApplication</code> también. Esto puede facilitar mucho la implementación en los tradicionales <code>Delegates</code> y <code>Activity</code> de iOS&#x2F;Android respectivamente, lo que nos permitiría tener personalizaciones con mucho menos código desde nuestro código multi-plataforma y próximas plataformas que se sumen a la iniciativa. </p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="500" height="379" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/hello-world-3.webp" alt="Maui" title="Maui" /><p>En lugar de Renderers, los Handlers sacan provecho del <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/mac/project-multitargeting?view=vsmac-2019">multi-targeting</a> para poder acceder directamente a los controles nativos de la plataforma (.NET para iOS y .NET para Android, y así sucesivamente) y poder acceder sin mucho intermediario los objetos que Xamarin nos ha permitido acceder desde C# tradicionalmente.</p><p>Veamos como quedaría la implementación de nuestro propio botón y definir un Handler para definir sus atributos.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="500" height="464" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/hello-world-4.webp" alt="Maui renderer" title="Maui renderer" /><p><strong>¿Qué esperar de esto a futuro en Maui?</strong> </p><ul><li>Con la estructura unificada de proyecto y la “extinción de los Renderers”, no solamente ganamos en facilidad de implementación, también es una mejora en rendimiento (sujeta a comprobación eventualmente, claro está) con todo lo que desde ya <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/performance-improvements-in-net-5/">se está logrando en desempeño con la version 5 de .NET</a>. </li><li>Como ya se anunció, MVVM y XAML no serán los únicos modos de desarrollar aplicaciones Maui, ya que se espera que tendremos la característica de desarrollo de aplicaciones MVU (Model-View-Update) y Blazor (Razor) sean soportadas. </li><li>Además del ya soportado C# Markup (disponible ahora en <a href="https://github.com/xamarin/XamarinCommunityToolkit">Xamarin Community Toolkit</a>) se espera que las aplicaciones declarativas con C# con HotReload sean de las características más prominentes para la plataforma. Más que una moda, el poder permitir nuevas formas de desarrollar viniendo de otros lenguajes, MVU y la misma web se vuelven una excelente forma de ampliar el uso .NET en todos lados.</li></ul><h2 id="4-Corriendo-el-proyecto"><a href="#4-Corriendo-el-proyecto" class="headerlink" title="4- Corriendo el proyecto"></a>4- Corriendo el proyecto</h2><p>Para este ejemplo usaremos el tooling actual desde VS para Mac y vemos que es posible correrlo sin problemas.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="350" height="500" src="/2020/12/03/Primer-vistazo-a-Net-Maui-con-codigo-Xamarin-Forms/hello-world-run-android.webp" alt="Hello World run" title="Hello World run" /><p><strong>¿Qué esperar de esto a futuro en Maui?</strong></p><ul><li>Maui en su momento lográ tener feature-parity (igualdad de características) y lograr mucho mejor desempeño (al que ya tiene ya de por sí) al que se tiene hoy en día para desarrollar aplicaciones Android, iOS, UWP y otras plataformas. </li><li>Además, no tendremos que preocuparnos por tener que implementar Handlers complejos o la apariencia multi-plataforma que realmente necesitemos hacerlo, lo cual terminaríamos haciendo (si fuera el caso) a un nivel nativo mediante las mismas APIs de las plataformas móviles.</li></ul><h2 id="5-Conclusiones-del-experimento"><a href="#5-Conclusiones-del-experimento" class="headerlink" title="5. Conclusiones del experimento."></a>5. Conclusiones del experimento.</h2><ul><li>Dado la velocidad que esta teniendo el proyecto Maui y las fechas de publicación de este artículo, pueda que muchos conceptos cambien y evolucionen a ideas mucho mas eficientes e innovadoras.</li><li>Como era de esperar, mucho del código utilizado para este ejemplo es inicial y proviene mayormente de Xamarin.Forms originalmente pero nos da un pequeño vistazo de las grandes cosas que se vienen para .NET y Maui. </li><li>Si bien se espera que mucha de la estructura y conceptos prevalezcan, pueda que varios de los componentes cambien con el tiempo naturalmente por componentes sucesores en la tecnología, y lo más importante, el Core mantiene su integridad. De ahí la importancia de que Maui esté en un repositorio complemamente aparte sin que afecte las versiones actuales de Xamarin.Forms y lo que venga en el próximo año.</li><li>El código base y los Handlers lucen bastante prometedor. Y no sólo desde allí, podemos esperar bastantes mejoras en el tooling actual hasta el punto que alcance todo lo necesario para que Maui tenga mucho más valor.</li></ul><h2 id="Recapitulando"><a href="#Recapitulando" class="headerlink" title="Recapitulando:"></a>Recapitulando:</h2><ul><li>Estructura unificada de proyecto </li><li>Mas plantillas desde la CLI para generar los proyectos (linux incluso y su creciente soporte en GTK)</li><li>Nuevos mecanismos de soporte para correr desde la CLI y VS Code (GitHub actions, App Center, Azure DevOps)</li><li>Y por último y no menos esperado: Hot-reload basado C# directamente!</li></ul><h2 id="5-Recursos-adicionales-y-recomendaciones"><a href="#5-Recursos-adicionales-y-recomendaciones" class="headerlink" title="5- Recursos adicionales y recomendaciones"></a>5- Recursos adicionales y recomendaciones</h2><ul><li>Codigo del playground en GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet-maui-playground">https://github.com/stvansolano/dotnet-maui-playground</a></li><li><a href="https://javiersuarezruiz.wordpress.com/2020/05/19/aloha-maui/">Introducción de .NET Multi-platform App UI</a> | Javier Suarez Ruiz</li><li><a href="https://javiersuarezruiz.wordpress.com/2020/06/15/videoblog-introduccion-a-net-maui/">Vlog - Introducción a .NET MAUI</a> | Javier Suarez Ruiz</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zZ_cdaN2qao">.NET Maui hacking!</a> | James Clancey - Maui + Comet + MVU</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qbHO8J3bId0">Introducing .NET Maui</a> | David Ortinau en YouTube</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Demos un vistazo preliminar a .NET Maui previo a los primeros previews que estaran disponibles a la comunidad proximamente! Codigo y baterias incluidas!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="Maui" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Maui/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Creating your first GitHub codespace for F# and .Net 5.0</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/</id>
    <published>2020-11-30T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.507Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s create our own F# codespace that can be used as a GitHub template to allow others to roll-up their own F#, .NET 5 based repositories!</p><!-- more --><blockquote><p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> GitHub Codespaces (GHCS) enables developers to create its own environments based on Open Source and Docker containers to tailor your development environments. You can get early access to GHCS from <a href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">this link</a> and try this sample from <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/fsharp-codespace">this</a> link from my GitHub account.</p></blockquote><h2 id="Give-F-amp-Codespaces-it-a-try"><a href="#Give-F-amp-Codespaces-it-a-try" class="headerlink" title="Give F# &amp; Codespaces it a try!"></a>Give F# &amp; Codespaces it a try!</h2><p>This blog entry is part of the <a href="https://sergeytihon.com/2020/10/22/f-advent-calendar-in-english-2020/">F# Calendar of Advent 2020 organized by Sergey Tihon in his blog</a>. Check out the full calendar post and spread the word!</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/preview.webp" alt="FSharp codespace" title="FSharp codespace" /><p>If you are new to F# like me, keep in mind that there are plenty of online tools and tips to learn F# direcly in the browser. Here are some available from F# Foundation and MSFT docs websites: </p><ul><li><a href="https://fsharp.org/learn/">https://fsharp.org/learn/</a></li><li><a href="https://try.fsharp.org/">https://try.fsharp.org/</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/fsharp/get-started/get-started-command-line?WT.mc_id=DT-MVP-5002082">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/fsharp/get-started/get-started-command-line</a></li></ul><p>For this post, we will:</p><ol><li>Take a base GitHub Codespace template (or create your own)</li><li>Hit the Code-&gt;Run in Codespace </li><li>Start coding!</li></ol><p>Let’s get it started!</p><h2 id="1-Take-a-base-GitHub-Codespace-template-or-create-your-own"><a href="#1-Take-a-base-GitHub-Codespace-template-or-create-your-own" class="headerlink" title="1. Take a base GitHub Codespace template (or create your own)"></a>1. Take a base GitHub Codespace template (or create your own)</h2><p>Let’s create our own F#, .NET 5 codespace that can be used as a GitHub template to allow others to roll-up their own repositories. </p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="500" height="225" src="/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/codespace-structure.png" alt="Codespace structure" title="Codespace structure" /><p>Most of the files needed live inside the <code>.devcontainer</code> folder structure. It needs to be at the root level in order to GHCS to understand it:</p><ul><li><code>Dockerfile</code> - A standard Docker file that will be taken by GHCS infrastructure. No prior knowledge of Docker is require to this, but it worths to mention. You can extend this file and include things based on your needs.</li><li><code>library-scripts</code> - Just a folder where we can place specific <code>bash</code> scripts that will be run by our Dockerfile</li><li><code>devcontainer.json</code> - A special JSON file that tells the Codespace. For this codespace, we will include some F# goodies to make it easier for starters:</li></ul><p>For the <code>Dockerfile</code> we will use the following Codespace Base image (Docker):</p><figure class="highlight routeros"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">ARG <span class="attribute">VARIANT</span>=3.1</span><br><span class="line"><span class="keyword">FROM</span> mcr.microsoft.com/vscode/devcontainers/dotnetcore:<span class="variable">$&#123;VARIANT&#125;</span></span><br><span class="line"><span class="comment"># ..</span></span><br><span class="line"></span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><blockquote><p>As you may expect, changing the VARIANT to 5 is the only change that we need in case we need to upgrade this environment so .NET 5 will be out of the box!</p></blockquote><p>For the <code>dev-container.json</code> file, you can get a closer look to the following section:</p><figure class="highlight 1c"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line"><span class="comment">// Add the IDs of extensions you want.</span></span><br><span class="line"><span class="string">&quot;extensions&quot;</span>: [</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;ms-azuretools.vscode-docker&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;ms-dotnettools.csharp&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;github.github-vscode-theme&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;coenraads.bracket-pair-colorizer-2&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;github.vscode-pull-request-github&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;ms-azuretools.vscode-docker&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;ms-vsliveshare.vsliveshare&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;vscode-icons-team.vscode-icons&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;visualstudioexptteam.vscodeintellicode&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;ms-azuretools.vscode-docker&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;vscode-icons-team.vscode-icons&quot;</span>,</span><br><span class="line">    <span class="string">&quot;ionide.ionide-fsharp&quot;</span></span><br><span class="line">],</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p><strong>Important:</strong> If you want to extend this workspace or getting more familiar with GHCS under the hood, I highly recommend you to check out the <code>dev-containers</code> repo from GitHub and Visual Studio Code documentation:</p><h3 id="VS-Code-x2F-Dev-Containers"><a href="#VS-Code-x2F-Dev-Containers" class="headerlink" title="- VS Code &#x2F; Dev Containers"></a>- VS Code &#x2F; Dev Containers</h3><p><a href="https://github.com/microsoft/vscode-dev-containers">https://github.com/microsoft/vscode-dev-containers</a></p><h3 id="VS-Code-x2F-Codespaces"><a href="#VS-Code-x2F-Codespaces" class="headerlink" title="- VS Code &#x2F; Codespaces"></a>- VS Code &#x2F; Codespaces</h3><p><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/remote/codespaces">https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/remote/codespaces</a></p><p>There you can find a big list of pre-defined images and great resources in case you want to go deep with other Docker supported technologies.</p><p>After this, we can stage-commit-push our changes and make the repo ready to go as a Template from GitHub.</p><h2 id="2-Hit-the-Code-gt-Run-in-Codespace-GHCS-access-required"><a href="#2-Hit-the-Code-gt-Run-in-Codespace-GHCS-access-required" class="headerlink" title="2. Hit the Code-&gt;Run in Codespace (GHCS access required)"></a>2. Hit the Code-&gt;Run in Codespace (GHCS access required)</h2><p>At this point, it will just need to get some minutes to let GitHub Codespaces to take all the source, build your codespace and let it bring it to you:</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="500" height="420" src="/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/codespace-ready.png" alt="Codespace ready" title="Codespace ready" /><h2 id="3-Start-coding"><a href="#3-Start-coding" class="headerlink" title="3. Start coding!"></a>3. Start coding!</h2><p>Let’s check everything to get our hands into the code:</p><p><code>dotnet --version</code></p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="384" src="/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/codespace-check.png" alt="Codespace check" title="Codespace check" /><p>Then let’s create our first F# project from the command line:</p><p><code>dotnet new console -lang &quot;F#&quot; HelloWorld</code></p><p>If you have coded with VSCode in the past, it brings a easy ready-to-run interface where we can include extensions from community. Earlier in this post, we had <code>ionide.ionide-fsharp</code> so it makes super easy to have our program up &amp; running with the ‘Play button’:</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="500" height="420" src="/2020/11/30/Creating-your-first-GitHub-codespace-for-F-Sharp-and-Net/codespace-run.png" alt="Codespace run" title="Codespace run" /><p>Thus, you can place breakpoints!</p><p>And that’s it! Happy coding!</p><h3 id="Recommended-links"><a href="#Recommended-links" class="headerlink" title="Recommended links"></a>Recommended links</h3><ul><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/fsharp/get-started/get-started-command-line?WT.mc_id=DT-MVP-5002082">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/fsharp/get-started/get-started-command-line</a></li><li><a href="https://fsharp.org/learn/">https://fsharp.org/learn/</a></li><li><a href="https://try.fsharp.org/">https://try.fsharp.org/</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/fsharp/get-started/get-started-command-line">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/fsharp/get-started/get-started-command-line</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/microsoft/vscode-dev-containers">https://github.com/microsoft/vscode-dev-containers</a></li><li><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/remote/codespaces">https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/remote/codespaces</a></li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Create our own F# codespace that can be used as a GitHub template to allow others to roll-up their own F#, .NET 5 based repositories!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="REST" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/REST/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="containers" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/containers/"/>
    
    <category term="Codespaces" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Codespaces/"/>
    
    <category term="Github" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Github/"/>
    
    <category term="FSharp" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/FSharp/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resumen y contenidos de mi charla - Mockeando tus APIs con C# y Xamarin DotNet Conf Latam</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/11/14/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Mockeando-APIs-con-CSharp-y-Xamarin-DotNet-Conf-Latam/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/11/14/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Mockeando-APIs-con-CSharp-y-Xamarin-DotNet-Conf-Latam/</id>
    <published>2020-11-14T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.543Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Comparto las diapositivas, links, codigo en GitHub y mas detalles de la .NET Conf y la edicion especial en formato online para Latinoamérica. ¡Gracias comunidad Latina .NET!</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Sobre-el-evento-¡Viva-NET"><a href="#Sobre-el-evento-¡Viva-NET" class="headerlink" title="Sobre el evento: ¡Viva .NET!"></a>Sobre el evento: ¡Viva .NET!</h2><p>Esta semana tuvo sede la .NET Conf a nivel mundial y desde hace más de 10 años en formato online, uno de los eventos más esperados por la comunidad .NET, celebrando a la vez el release de .NET 5, la tan esperada unificación de la plataforma bajo 1 solo .NET (no mas .NET Framework ni .NET Core en adelante, solo .NET).</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2020/11/14/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Mockeando-APIs-con-CSharp-y-Xamarin-DotNet-Conf-Latam/talk.png" alt="DotNet Conf Latam" title="DotNet Conf Latam" /><blockquote><p>Link de la transmisión al evento completo (YouTube): <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wcVrXGlxZxA">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wcVrXGlxZxA</a></p></blockquote><p>Para la comunidad latina, tuvimos el privilegio de ser enlace y transmitidos como parte de las sesiones complementarias al evento global en conjunto con la organización de la comunidad Latino .NET Online quien se encargó de reunir la agenda y speakers del área que frecuentamos compartir con esta gran comunidad, abarcando casi 8h completas de transmisión continua y +1800 vistas en YouTube de todo el evento.</p><iframe width="400" height="338" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wcVrXGlxZxA?start=20144" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe><blockquote><p>Especial agradecimiento y créditos en todo momento a <a href="https://latinonet.online/">Latino .NET Online</a> por su labor titánica para realizar este evento.</p></blockquote><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Do it amigo! We have <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dotnetconf?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#dotnetconf</a> content waiting for you guys!<a href="https://t.co/Y4DDWR4wCI">https://t.co/Y4DDWR4wCI</a><a href="https://t.co/Y4DDWR4wCI">https://t.co/Y4DDWR4wCI</a></p>&mdash; Esteban Solano G. 🇨🇷 (@stvansolano) <a href="https://twitter.com/stvansolano/status/1327982486559858690?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 15, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><h3 id="Diapositivas-y-video-de-mi-presentacion-Mockeando-tus-APIs-con-C-y-Xamarin"><a href="#Diapositivas-y-video-de-mi-presentacion-Mockeando-tus-APIs-con-C-y-Xamarin" class="headerlink" title="Diapositivas y video de mi presentación: Mockeando tus APIs con C# y Xamarin"></a>Diapositivas y video de mi presentación: Mockeando tus APIs con C# y Xamarin</h3><p>El día estuvo cargado de sesiones, abarcando desarrollo web, .NET 5, Xamarin, Blazor, Azure y muchos más. Les comparto el link en caso que no pudieran asistir. En mi presentación, aporté con mi charla titulada “Mockeando tus APIs con C# y Xamarin”.</p><p>Por acá el link de descarga (click derecho, descargar) a las diapositivas:<br><a href="https://files.speakerdeck.com/presentations/4cc7867410c641e680a45f8d3fd60e34/NetConf2020.pdf">Diapositivas</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/mockeando-tus-apis-con-c-number-y-xamarin-b126f92b-a34f-47c5-ac45-5b2062fb56cb&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><blockquote><p>Esta charla tuve oportunidad de presentarla en la DotNetCoreConf meses atrás, en donde hice la demo y presentación desde Visual Studio para Mac</p></blockquote><iframe width="400" height="338" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_-FzKgVl03g?autoplay=0&fs=0&iv_load_policy=3&showinfo=0&rel=0&cc_load_policy=0&start=0&end=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe><p>Presentación para la DotNetConf 2020 Virtual: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_-FzKgVl03g">https://www.youtube.com/embed/_-FzKgVl03g</a></p><h3 id="Codigo-fuente-GitHub"><a href="#Codigo-fuente-GitHub" class="headerlink" title="Codigo fuente (GitHub)"></a>Codigo fuente (GitHub)</h3><p>Por aca el link al repositorio en mi GitHub con todo el material.</p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/WooCommerce-Mobile">https://github.com/stvansolano/WooCommerce-Mobile</a></p><h2 id="Documentacion-WooCommerce-WordPress"><a href="#Documentacion-WooCommerce-WordPress" class="headerlink" title="Documentación WooCommerce (WordPress)"></a>Documentación WooCommerce (WordPress)</h2><p>El ejemplo que mostré está basado en la implementación del API para la tienda en línea de WooCommerce (Tienda Open Source basada en WordPress), la cual tuve oportunidad de crear la aplicación y conectarla al backend hospedado todo en Azure. Les dejo por acá el link a la documentación, la cual utilicé para “mockearla” para la demo.</p><p><a href="http://woocommerce.github.io/woocommerce-rest-api-docs/">http://woocommerce.github.io/woocommerce-rest-api-docs/</a></p><h3 id="By-the-Community-For-the-Community"><a href="#By-the-Community-For-the-Community" class="headerlink" title="By the Community, For the Community!"></a>By the Community, For the Community!</h3><p>Agradecerles nuevamente a todos los organizadores, speakers y entusiastas que participaron en la realización del evento! Les invito a suscribirte a mi blog <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">en este link</a> y a mantenernos en contacto para vernos en próximas actividades!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Comparto las diapositivas, links, codigo en GitHub y mas detalles de la .NET Conf y la edicion especial en formato online para Latinoamérica. ¡Gracias comunidad Latina .NET!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
    <category term="Serverless" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Serverless/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mobile Workshop (Online): Xamarin Intro (2020)</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/08/18/Mobile-Workshop-Online-Xamarin-Intro/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/08/18/Mobile-Workshop-Online-Xamarin-Intro/</id>
    <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.527Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sharing Slides + recording + GitHub Code - Mobile CR Developers meetup</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Mobile-CR-Developers-Meetup-online"><a href="#Mobile-CR-Developers-Meetup-online" class="headerlink" title="Mobile CR Developers - Meetup online:"></a>Mobile CR Developers - Meetup online:</h2><p>Mobile Workshop (Online): Xamarin Intro (2020)</p><h3 id="Slides"><a href="#Slides" class="headerlink" title="Slides"></a>Slides</h3><p>(right-click, download):<br><a href="https://files.speakerdeck.com/presentations/3f375c3458794aa4a87bf91176c94a45/Mobile_Workshop_-_Xamarin_Intro_2020.pdf">Slides</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/mobile-workshop-xamarin-intro&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h3 id="Source-code-GitHub"><a href="#Source-code-GitHub" class="headerlink" title="Source code (GitHub)"></a>Source code (GitHub)</h3><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/MobileWorkshop">https://github.com/stvansolano/MobileWorkshop</a></p><h3 id="Contact-me"><a href="#Contact-me" class="headerlink" title="Contact me"></a>Contact me</h3><p><a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">Subscribe to my blog!</a> </p><p>Happy coding!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Sharing Slides + recording + GitHub Code - Mobile CR Developers meetup</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resumen y contenidos - Xamarin Assemble 2020 edicion online! 🙉⚡📱</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/07/20/Resumen-y-contenidos-Xamarin-Assemble-2020-Online/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/07/20/Resumen-y-contenidos-Xamarin-Assemble-2020-Online/</id>
    <published>2020-07-20T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.543Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Te perdiste Xamarin Assemble? Comparto mis diapositivas, links, codigo en GitHub y mas detalles del Xamarin Assemble 2020 Online. Gracias a todos&#x2F;as por acompañarnos!</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Sobre-el-evento"><a href="#Sobre-el-evento" class="headerlink" title="Sobre el evento"></a>Sobre el evento</h2><p>El pasado 16, 17 y 18 de julio de 2020 tuve la oportunidad de participar en el Xamarin Assemble, el evento de Xamarin &#x2F; Mobile Cross Platform más grande de Argentina, y por primera vez en su versión en línea!</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2020/07/20/Resumen-y-contenidos-Xamarin-Assemble-2020-Online/preview.webp" alt="Xamarin Assemble 2020 Online" title="Xamarin Assemble 2020 Online" /><blockquote><p>Website: <a href="https://www.xamarinassemble.com/">https://www.xamarinassemble.com/</a></p></blockquote><p>Para esta ocasión el evento contó con 28 speakers y en especial con la participacion destacada miembros del equipo de Xamarin incluyendo David Ortinau, James Montemagno, Maddy Leger, Brandon Minnick y por supuesto MVPS y entusiastas de la comunidad Xamarin de toda Latinoamerica y de todo el mundo.</p><p>De mi parte, muy agradecido con los organizadores por permitirme sumar a este tipo de eventos y felicitarlos por llevar a cabo la actividad a lo largo de 3 dias, con más de 900 espectadores y 20 sesiones.</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Aaaand that&#39;s a wrap! THANK YOU everyone for joining us and being part of this awesome event! 👏📲🤗 <a href="https://twitter.com/XamarinAssemble?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@XamarinAssemble</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/sebaleoperez?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@sebaleoperez</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/fede_macca?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@fede_macca</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/germankuber?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@germankuber</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/Micaela_Perdomo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@Micaela_Perdomo</a> <a href="https://t.co/Q0IpVTPc3X">pic.twitter.com/Q0IpVTPc3X</a></p>&mdash; Nico Milcoff (@nmilcoff) <a href="https://twitter.com/nmilcoff/status/1284595076660944902?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 18, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><h3 id="Diapositivas-de-mi-presentacion-Desarrollo-de-apps-real’time-con-Xamarin-CosmosDB-y-SignalR"><a href="#Diapositivas-de-mi-presentacion-Desarrollo-de-apps-real’time-con-Xamarin-CosmosDB-y-SignalR" class="headerlink" title="Diapositivas de mi presentación: Desarrollo de apps real’time con Xamarin, CosmosDB y SignalR"></a>Diapositivas de mi presentación: Desarrollo de apps real’time con Xamarin, CosmosDB y SignalR</h3><p>Por acá el link de descarga (click derecho, descargar):<br><a href="https://files.speakerdeck.com/presentations/9558f6b7d4f04a5689d1038bb6f3e9a1/Xamarin-Assemble-SignalR-CosmosDB-Xamarin.pdf">Diapositivas</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/xamarinassemble-desarrollo-de-aplicaciones-real-time-con-xamarin-signalr-y-cosmosdb&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h3 id="Codigo-fuente-GitHub"><a href="#Codigo-fuente-GitHub" class="headerlink" title="Codigo fuente (GitHub)"></a>Codigo fuente (GitHub)</h3><p>Por aca el link al repositorio en mi GitHub con todo el material.</p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/my-todo-app">https://github.com/stvansolano/my-todo-app</a></p><h3 id="By-the-Community-For-the-Community"><a href="#By-the-Community-For-the-Community" class="headerlink" title="By the Community, For the Community!"></a>By the Community, For the Community!</h3><p>Agradecerles nuevamente a todos los organizadores, speakers y entusiastas que participaron en la realización del evento! Estare actualizando este post con mas detalles del evento y la grabacion, en cuanto se encuentren disponibles. Mientras tanto les invito a suscribirte a mi blog <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">en este link</a> y a mantenernos en contacto para vernos en próximas actividades.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Te perdiste Xamarin Assemble? Comparto mis diapositivas, links, codigo en GitHub y mas detalles del Xamarin Assemble 2020 Online. Gracias a todos/as por acompañarnos!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
    <category term="Serverless" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Serverless/"/>
    
    <category term="SignalR" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/SignalR/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Guia de CSharp 8 y NET 5: primeros pasos y recomendaciones</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/04/11/Guia-de-CSharp-8-9-y-NET-5-primeros-pasos-y-recomendaciones/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/04/11/Guia-de-CSharp-8-9-y-NET-5-primeros-pasos-y-recomendaciones/</id>
    <published>2020-04-11T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.515Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ya probaste o estas usando NET 5? Conoce las novedades del lenguaje C# y lo que viene nuevo para el lenguaje CSharp y .NET 5 (codigo fuente incluido!)</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Sobre-el-evento"><a href="#Sobre-el-evento" class="headerlink" title="Sobre el evento"></a>Sobre el evento</h2><p>Para el mes de abril tuvimos un livestream con la comunidad Latino .NET Online en donde comparti lo ultimo hasta la fecha en cuanto a NET 5, lo ultimo en temas de .NET el cual se espera liberar para noviembre de 2020.</p><p>Si bien todo está como Preview (2) por estas fechas, es posible acceder a los binarios del SDK de .NET 5 e incluso probarlo desde contenedores Docker, por lo que decidí darle un vistazo y de paso compartir sobre las novedades que introdujo C# 8 y lo que está a la vista para la versión 9 del lenguaje.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="330" src="/2020/04/11/Guia-de-CSharp-8-9-y-NET-5-primeros-pasos-y-recomendaciones/preview.webp" alt="CSharp 8 y NET 5" title="CSharp 8 y NET 5" /><p>Para la demo, construí un repositorio recopilando varios contenidos, entre ellos:</p><ul><li>Poderlo correr desde VSCode y la extensión de Remote Containers, esto con Docker<br>VSCode + Remote containers Computadora personal</li><li>EFCore 5 Preview (Que incorpora lo ultimo de Entity Framework y soporte para CosmosDB)</li><li>Una base de datos SQL Server linux disponible para el ambiente mediante Docker Compose</li><li>Ejemplos de Blazor Server y Blazor Web Assembly Template disponibles para .NET (Core en general)</li><li>Ejemplos de C# 8 con multi-targeting para NET Core 3.1 (actual) y NET 5 (futuro)</li></ul><p>Para los ejemplos de C# 8 decidí elegir 10 e incluirlos en el código para que sea fácil de utilizar, compilarlo y correrlo.</p><ol><li>Using-Declarations</li><li>Default-Interface-Methods</li><li>Switch-Expressions</li><li>Property-Patterns</li><li>Tuple-Patterns</li><li>Positional-Patterns</li><li>Static-Local-Functions</li><li>Async-Streams</li><li>Indexes-And-Ranges</li><li>Coalescing-Assignment</li></ol><p>Te invito a bajar el repositorio y explorar los contenidos desde este link: </p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/csharp-sandbox/tree/master/samples/CSharp8-Examples">https://github.com/stvansolano/csharp-sandbox/tree/master/samples/CSharp8-Examples</a></p><p>Te recomiendo también darle un vistazo al archivo <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/csharp-sandbox/blob/master/README.md">README.md</a> del proyecto en donde coloqué los pasos para correr los contenedores y los ejemplos.</p><p>Si bien utilizar Docker para este tipo de pruebas puede sonar demasiado laborioso, se me hizo sencillo e interesante de probar todo junto con la extensión de remote containers de VSCode, así como usar Docker Compose para levantar un contenedor de SQL Server Linux como había hecho en otras sesiones y ponerlo a trabajar todo junto con Web API y EF Core5 (también en Preview).</p><p>No sólo eso, sino que poder componer un Azure DevOps pipeline se vuelve súper fácil y en cuestión de minutos se puede hacer push a un Azure Container Instance y ponerlo a correr en Azure en un par de clicks&#x2F;commits al repositorio.</p><h2 id="Grabacion-de-la-charla"><a href="#Grabacion-de-la-charla" class="headerlink" title="Grabacion de la charla"></a>Grabacion de la charla</h2><p>Aún no está disponible la grabación pero estaré actualizando este post en cuanto esté disponible.</p><p>El código de la demo disponible en mi GitHub desde la dirección: <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/csharp-sandbox/">https://github.com/stvansolano/csharp-sandbox/</a> </p><h2 id="Diapositivas-de-la-charla"><a href="#Diapositivas-de-la-charla" class="headerlink" title="Diapositivas de la charla"></a>Diapositivas de la charla</h2><p><a href="https://speakerd.s3.amazonaws.com/presentations/2a21c3c3e541446da2112cdea4d5128f/CSharp8_y_NET_5.pdf">PDF</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/c-number-8-and-net-5-primeros-pasos&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h2 id="Agradecimiento"><a href="#Agradecimiento" class="headerlink" title="Agradecimiento"></a>Agradecimiento</h2><p>Muchas gracias a la comunidad Latino .NET Online por la difusión del contenido y a todos&#x2F;as los que atendieron la actividad!</p><p>Estaré actualizando este post con el resto del material utilizado, scripts y codigo que use en la presentacion. Te invito a suscribirte a mi blog <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">en este link</a> y a mantenernos en contacto.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Ya probaste o estas usando NET 5? Conoce las novedades del lenguaje C# y lo que viene nuevo para el lenguaje CSharp y .NET 5 (codigo fuente incluido!)</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="REST" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/REST/"/>
    
    <category term="Comunidad" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Comunidad/"/>
    
    <category term="Online" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Online/"/>
    
    <category term="WebAPI" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/WebAPI/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resumen y contenidos charla DotNetConf Latam 2020: Xamarin Real-time mobile apps con CosmosDB y SignalR</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/03/28/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-DotNetConf-Latam-real-time-mobile-apps-xamarin-cosmosdb-signalr/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/03/28/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-DotNetConf-Latam-real-time-mobile-apps-xamarin-cosmosdb-signalr/</id>
    <published>2020-03-28T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.543Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Comparto las diapositivas, links, video y codigo en GitHub de mi participacion en el DotNet Conf Latam Online 2020. Gracias a todos&#x2F;as por participar!</p><!-- more --><h2 id="Sobre-el-evento"><a href="#Sobre-el-evento" class="headerlink" title="Sobre el evento"></a>Sobre el evento</h2><p>El mes de marzo se realizo la .NET Conf Online: Focus on Xamarin, en donde profesionales y entusiastas de estas tecnologías compartieron sus conocimientos y mejores prácticas en el desarrollo de aplciaciones móviles nativas con Xamarin.</p><p>Para Latam, Luis Beltrán y Humberto Jaimes corrieron con el evento de manera en línea, con más de 10 horas continuas de transmisión con miembros de la comunindad Latinoamericana de .NET</p><p>Para mi charla hablé sobre desarrollo Serverless con Azure y Xamarin, utilizando SignalR, CosmosDB todo sobre Azure Functions en la nube.</p><iframe width="400" height="338" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/s_zZ7ALiNJQ?start=29" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><p>El código de la demo disponible en mi GitHub desde la dirección: <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/my-todo-app/">https://github.com/stvansolano/my-todo-app/</a> (carpeta Serverless&#x2F;SignalR)</p><h2 id="Agenda-del-evento"><a href="#Agenda-del-evento" class="headerlink" title="Agenda del evento"></a>Agenda del evento</h2><p>Saturday, 28 March 2020</p><ul><li><p>8:15amKeynote Bienvenida al evento</p></li><li><p>8:30amConectando apps móviles Xamarin Forms con Azure Functions (serverless) Eduardo Barrios - .NET Developer (Guatemala)</p></li><li><p>9:20amXamarin Forms Best Practices Charlin Agramonte y Rendy Del Rosario Microsoft MVPs (República Dominicana)</p></li><li><p>10:10amIntegrando AzureAD a tus aplicaciones de Xamarin.Forms Jesus Angulo - Microsoft MVP (Perú)</p></li><li><p>11:00amData Binding for Xamarin Forms In-Depth Alejandro Ruiz Varela - Microsoft MVP (México)</p></li><li><p>11:50amCómo crear un control XAML perzonalizado Humberto Jaimes - Microsoft MVP (México)</p></li><li><p>12:40pmCI&#x2F;CD en Xamarin apps con GitHub, Bitrise y AppCenter Cristian González - Xamarin Developer (México)</p></li><li><p>1:30pmDesarrollo de aplicaciones Real-time con Xamarin y CosmosDB Esteban Solano Granados - Microsoft MVP (Costa Rica)</p></li><li><p>2:20pmMejores prácticas de T-SQL para Developers Jesús Gil - Microsoft MVP (México)</p></li><li><p>3:10pmExplorando Xamarin.Forms CarouselView Luis Beltrán - Microsoft MVP (México)</p></li><li><p>4:00pmValidación de formularios con Xamarin Forms Héctor Pérez - Xamarin Trainer (México)</p></li><li><p>4:50pmCierre del evento</p></li></ul><h3 id="Diapositivas"><a href="#Diapositivas" class="headerlink" title="Diapositivas:"></a>Diapositivas:</h3><p>Por acá el PDF - <a href="https://speakerd.s3.amazonaws.com/presentations/a02b51ee905d4c5ba23a83f302d78dab/NET_Conf_Focus_Latam.pdf">Link de descarga.</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/desarrollo-de-aplicaciones-real-time-con-xamarin-y-cosmosdb&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h2 id="Agradecimiento"><a href="#Agradecimiento" class="headerlink" title="Agradecimiento"></a>Agradecimiento</h2><p>Muchas gracias a las más de 300 personas registradas al evento, a Luis Beltrán y Humberto Jaimes por la excelente organización antes y durante el evento y a todos&#x2F;as los asistentes de la actividad!</p><p>Estaré actualizando este post con el resto del material utilizado, scripts y codigo que use en la presentacion. Te invito a suscribirte a mi blog <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">en este link</a> y a mantenernos en contacto.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Comparto las diapositivas, links, video y codigo en GitHub de mi participacion en el DotNet Conf Latam Online 2020. Gracias a todos/as por participar!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="Mobile" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Mobile/"/>
    
    <category term="Serverless" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Serverless/"/>
    
    <category term="SignalR" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/SignalR/"/>
    
    <category term="CosmosDB" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/CosmosDB/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resumen y contenidos - Charla Open Data Day 2020 Costa Rica: Intro a Inteligencia Artificial y Aprendizaje Maquina (Azure)</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/03/07/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Open-Data-Day-2020-Costa-Rica-Intro-Machine-Learning-en-la-nube-azure/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/03/07/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Open-Data-Day-2020-Costa-Rica-Intro-Machine-Learning-en-la-nube-azure/</id>
    <published>2020-03-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.547Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Comparto las diapositivas, links, codigo en GitHub de la charla impartida como parte del Open Data Day 2020 Costa Rica: Intro a Inteligencia Artificial y Aprendizaje Maquina (Azure). Gracias a todos&#x2F;as por acompañarnos!</p><!-- more --><p>El sábado 7 de marzo de 2020 tuve la oportunidad de dar una charla introductoria sobre Inteligencia Artificial y Aprendizaje Máquina (Machine Learning), donde pude demostrar el uso de tecnologías modernas aplicadas incluyendo Python, Jupyter Notebooks, Docker y Visual Studio Code y sus extensión para Machine Learning.</p><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2020/03/07/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Open-Data-Day-2020-Costa-Rica-Intro-Machine-Learning-en-la-nube-azure/preview.webp" alt="Open Data Day 2020" title="Open Data Day 2020" /><p>Muy agradecido con la organización por permitirme llevar este tipo de contenidos y llevar a cabo la actividad en 3 salas simulateamente y llena de actividades como parte del Día Mundial de los Datos.</p><h3 id="Diapositivas"><a href="#Diapositivas" class="headerlink" title="Diapositivas:"></a>Diapositivas:</h3><p>Por acá el link de descarga (click derecho, descargar):<br><a href="https://speakerd.s3.amazonaws.com/presentations/5ec63879f2ee434d9b4c76d0fb969cdf/Intro_AI_y_Machine_Learning-2.pdf">Diapositivas</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/introduccion-a-inteligencia-artificial-y-aprendizaje-maquina-en-la-nube&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h3 id="Links-recomendados-y-extensiones"><a href="#Links-recomendados-y-extensiones" class="headerlink" title="Links recomendados y extensiones"></a>Links recomendados y extensiones</h3><p>Contenidos sobre Machine Learning</p><ul><li><a href="https://aischool.microsoft.com/en-us/search;searchString=machine%20learning">Microsoft AI School - Contenidos gratuitos</a></li><li><a href="http://ml.azure.com/">Microsoft Azure Learning</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/machine-learning/tutorial-setup-vscode-extension">Azure Machine Learning</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/es-es/azure/machine-learning/">Docs.microsoft.com - Machine Learning</a></li></ul><p>Como parte de las demos utilice mayormente VS Code y mi explorador, dejo por aca las extensiones recomendadas:</p><ul><li><a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=ms-toolsai.vscode-ai">Azure Machine Learning</a></li><li><a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=ms-python.python">Python Extension</a></li><li><a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=ms-vscode.azure-account">Azure Account</a></li></ul><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2020/03/07/Resumen-y-contenidos-charla-Open-Data-Day-2020-Costa-Rica-Intro-Machine-Learning-en-la-nube-azure/install-aml-vscode-extension.png" alt="Azure Machine Learning Extension" title="Azure Machine Learning Extension" /><h3 id="Codigo-fuente-GitHub"><a href="#Codigo-fuente-GitHub" class="headerlink" title="Codigo fuente (GitHub)"></a>Codigo fuente (GitHub)</h3><p>Por aca el link al repositorio en mi GitHub con todo el material.</p><p><a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/python-experiments">https://github.com/stvansolano/python-experiments</a></p><h3 id="Agradecimiento-y-proximas-meetups"><a href="#Agradecimiento-y-proximas-meetups" class="headerlink" title="Agradecimiento y proximas meetups"></a>Agradecimiento y proximas meetups</h3><p>Estare actualizando este post con el resto del material utilizado, scripts y codigo que use en la presentacion. Gracias a todos los asistentes y les invito a suscribirte a mi blog <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">en este link</a> y a mantenernos en contacto para vernos en proximas actividades.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Comparto las diapositivas, links, codigo en GitHub de la charla impartida como parte del Open Data Day 2020: Intro a Inteligencia Artificial y Aprendizaje Maquina. Gracias a todos/as por acompañarnos!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="OSS" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/OSS/"/>
    
    <category term="Azure" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Azure/"/>
    
    <category term="MachineLearning" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/MachineLearning/"/>
    
    <category term="Python" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Python/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Grabacion TechJam Nicaragua 2020 - Mobile Backends Docker, .NET Core, Xamarin y SQL Server en Linux</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/02/22/Grabacion-Nicaragua-TechJam-2020-Xamarin-Mobile-Backends-con-Docker/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2020/02/22/Grabacion-Nicaragua-TechJam-2020-Xamarin-Mobile-Backends-con-Docker/</id>
    <published>2020-02-22T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.515Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Comparto la grabación de mi charla del sábado 22 de febrero de 2020, donde la oportunidad de asistir como ponente remotamente en TechJam Nicaragua 2020. </p><!-- more --><h2 id="Sobre-el-evento"><a href="#Sobre-el-evento" class="headerlink" title="Sobre el evento"></a>Sobre el evento</h2><p>TechJam 2020 fue evento que consistió en 3 hilos de conferencias como parte de un mismo evento, interactuando con expositores de Nicaragua e invitados especiales incluyendo Microsoft MVPs y miembros de la .NET Foundation.</p><p>Mi charla se tituló: ** Mobile Backends - Docker, .NET Core + SQL Server (Linux)**</p><p>Como parte de la charla, mostré la utilización de Docker para crear imágenes de Docker basadas en SQL Server sobre linux, crear un backend de .NET Core y conectarlo con una aplicación Xamarin.Forms</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="es" dir="ltr">Gracias <a href="https://twitter.com/DotnetNicaragua?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DotnetNicaragua</a> por la invitación y coordinacion de los 3 tracks simultaneos con la comunidad. NET e invitados! <a href="https://twitter.com/dotnet?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@dotnet</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/dotnetfdn?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@dotnetfdn</a> <a href="https://t.co/bBfGJXfDRc">https://t.co/bBfGJXfDRc</a> <a href="https://t.co/GfxGJ8At8V">pic.twitter.com/GfxGJ8At8V</a></p>&mdash; Esteban Solano G. 🇨🇷 (@stvansolano) <a href="https://twitter.com/stvansolano/status/1231385399861370882?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 23, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><h2 id="Grabacion-disponible-en-YouTube"><a href="#Grabacion-disponible-en-YouTube" class="headerlink" title="Grabacion disponible en YouTube"></a>Grabacion disponible en YouTube</h2><p>Dejo por acá la grabación cortesía de la comunidad Nicaragua Developers:</p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dx64ItK2owk&quot; alt=&quot;YouTube&quot; title=&quot;YouTube&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h2 id="Agradecimiento"><a href="#Agradecimiento" class="headerlink" title="Agradecimiento"></a>Agradecimiento</h2><p>Muchas gracias a la organizacion de .NET Nicaragua por invitarme y a todos los participantes presenciales y remotos por atender!</p><h3 id="Diapositivas"><a href="#Diapositivas" class="headerlink" title="Diapositivas:"></a>Diapositivas:</h3><p>Por acá el <a href="https://speakerd.s3.amazonaws.com/presentations/69e7c3042ad04f49b04a9ef25e23e3d5/Mobile_backends_-_Docker__DotNet.pdf">Link de descarga.</a></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&lt;Link href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/mobile-backends-docker-net-core-plus-sql-server-linux&quot; alt=&quot;Link&quot; title=&quot;Link&quot; /&gt;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h3 id="Codigo-fuente"><a href="#Codigo-fuente" class="headerlink" title="Codigo fuente"></a>Codigo fuente</h3><p>Como parte del ejemplo mostré mi repositorio <code>XamarinExplorer</code> de donde puedes bajarte el branch de develop y explorar el Dockerfile, código de backend en .NET Core y la aplicación Xamarin</p><p>Link al código: <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/xamarin-explorer">XamarinExplorer en GitHub</a></p><h3 id="Mas-contenido-y-actividades"><a href="#Mas-contenido-y-actividades" class="headerlink" title="Más contenido y actividades"></a>Más contenido y actividades</h3><p>¡No olvides <a href="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/#suscribe">suscribirte</a> a mi blog para recibir noticias sobre próximos eventos y artículos que estaré publicando.</p><p>Nos vemos en la próxima!</p><p>Saludos</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Comparto la grabación de mi charla del sábado 22 de febrero de 2020, donde la oportunidad de asistir como ponente remotamente en TechJam Nicaragua 2020</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="DotNet" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/DotNet/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Speaking" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Speaking/"/>
    
    <category term="Conferences" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Conferences/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="REST" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/REST/"/>
    
    <category term="Comunidad" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Comunidad/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resumen - Actividades presenciales y en línea de Noviembre 2019. Slides, videos y más</title>
    <link href="http://stvansolano.github.io/2019/12/01/Resumen-Actividades-presenciales-y-en-linea-de-Noviembre-2019-Slides-videos-y-mas/"/>
    <id>http://stvansolano.github.io/2019/12/01/Resumen-Actividades-presenciales-y-en-linea-de-Noviembre-2019-Slides-videos-y-mas/</id>
    <published>2019-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T19:56:05.535Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Llegamos a la recta final del año 2019! Comparto algunas de las actividades, diapositivas y contenidos de mi actividad en temas de Azure, Xamarin, DevOps y otros mas!</p><!-- more --><img class="img-fluid box-shadow text-center" width="600" height="338" src="/2019/12/01/Resumen-Actividades-presenciales-y-en-linea-de-Noviembre-2019-Slides-videos-y-mas/preview.webp" alt="Azure" title="Azure" /><h2 id="Desarrollo-movil-Xamarin-con-Serverless-y-Docker-disponible-en-linea"><a href="#Desarrollo-movil-Xamarin-con-Serverless-y-Docker-disponible-en-linea" class="headerlink" title="Desarrollo móvil Xamarin con Serverless y Docker (disponible en línea)"></a>Desarrollo móvil Xamarin con Serverless y Docker (disponible en línea)</h2><h3 id="Video"><a href="#Video" class="headerlink" title="Video:"></a>Video:</h3><iframe width="400" height="338" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0XDMd2joRsM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><p>–<a href="https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/desarrollo-movil-con-serverless-docker-y-xamarin">Diapositivas</a> y <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/serverless-workshop">GitHub</a></p><h2 id="Introduccion-a-Mobile-DevOps-disponible-en-linea"><a href="#Introduccion-a-Mobile-DevOps-disponible-en-linea" class="headerlink" title="Introduccion a Mobile DevOps (disponible en línea)"></a>Introduccion a Mobile DevOps (disponible en línea)</h2><h3 id="Video-1"><a href="#Video-1" class="headerlink" title="Video:"></a>Video:</h3><iframe width="400" height="338" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vrkgSRV8zYU" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><ul><li><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/stvansolano/introduccion-a-mobile-devops">Diapositivas</a> y - - <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/xamarin-explorer">GitHub</a></li></ul><blockquote><p>Ambos videos formaron parte las sesiones del 3er aniversario de la <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/xamarindiplomadoitc/permalink/2481666665447512/">Comunidad Xamarin en Español</a> organizado por mis colegas MVP Luis Antonio Beltran y Humberto Jaimes a quienes agradezco muchísimo la invitación.</p></blockquote><h2 id="Meetup-Intro-a-Azure-DevOps-presencial"><a href="#Meetup-Intro-a-Azure-DevOps-presencial" class="headerlink" title="Meetup: Intro a Azure DevOps (presencial)"></a>Meetup: Intro a Azure DevOps (presencial)</h2><p>Tuve la oportunidad de iniciar una meetup de Azure para Costa Rica! Espero poder realizar más actividades en este tema y compartir&#x2F;combinar con lo que realizo en tecnonlogías de desarrollo de software.</p><p>Comencé Azure Costa Rica como un grupo abierto a charlas y temas orientado a principiantes, estudiantes y profesionales de computación que deseen compartir, aprender y incluso contribuir con la comunidad técnica en temas de Azure de cualquier tipo.</p><p>¿Te interesa impartir una charla o taller con la comunidad? Únete y entra en contacto!</p><ul><li>Lugar: CPIC Costa Rica (Gracias por hospedar esta meetup!)</li><li>Link a meetup: <a href="https://www.meetup.com/es-ES/Azure-Costa-Rica/">Azure Costa Rica</a></li><li>[Diapositivas](Intro a Azure DevOps y VS Online) y <a href="https://github.com/stvansolano/backend">GitHub</a></li></ul><h3 id="Agradecimiento-y-proximas-actividades"><a href="#Agradecimiento-y-proximas-actividades" class="headerlink" title="Agradecimiento y proximas actividades"></a>Agradecimiento y proximas actividades</h3><p>Gracias a todos los asistentes, y en especial a quienes abrieron espacio para hospedar mis sesiones en línea y presencial para Costa Rica.</p><p>Te invito a suscribirte a mi blog <a href="https://stvansolano.github.io/taller/#suscribe">en este link</a> y a mantenernos en contacto para vernos en proximas actividades.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">Llegamos a la recta final del año 2019! Comparto algunas de las actividades, diapositivas y contenidos de mi actividad en temas de Azure, Xamarin, DevOps y otros mas!</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Xamarin" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Xamarin/"/>
    
    <category term="Spanish/Español" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Spanish-Espanol/"/>
    
    <category term="Productividad" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Productividad/"/>
    
    <category term="Conferences" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Conferences/"/>
    
    <category term="Docker" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/Docker/"/>
    
    <category term="VisualStudio" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/VisualStudio/"/>
    
    <category term="NetCore" scheme="http://stvansolano.github.io/blog/tags/NetCore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
